<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Hassan Abedi&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://habedi.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Hassan Abedi&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 14:00:28 +0430</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://habedi.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>THE VALUE OF FREE THOUGHT</title>
      <link>http://habedi.github.io/post/value-of-free-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 14:00:28 +0430</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://habedi.github.io/post/value-of-free-thought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertrand_Russell&#34;&gt;Bertrand Russell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expression &amp;ldquo;free thought&amp;rdquo; is often used as if it meant merely opposition to the prevailing orthodoxy. But this is only a symptom of free thought, frequent, but invariable. &amp;ldquo;Free thought&amp;rdquo; means thinking  freely-as freely, at least, as is possible for a human being. The person  who is free in any respect is free from something; what is the free  thinker free from? To be worthy of the name, he must be free of two  things: the force of tradition, and the tyranny of his own passions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one is completely free from either, but in the measure of a man&amp;rsquo;s emancipation he deserves to be called a free thinker. A man is not to be denied this title because he happens, on some point, to agree with  the theologians of his country. An Arab who, starting from the first  principles of human reason, is able to deduce that the Koran was not created, but existed eternally in heaven, may be counted as a free  thinker, provided he is willing to listen to counter arguments and subject his ratiocination to critical scrutiny. On the same conditions, a European who, from a definition of benevolence, is able to show that a benevolent Deity will subject infants to an eternity of torment if they die before some one sprinkles them with water to the accompaniment of certain magical words, will have to be regarded as satisfying our definition. What makes a free thinker is not his beliefs, but the way in which he holds them. If he holds them because his elders told him they were true when he was young, or if he holds them because if he did not he would be unhappy, his thought is not free; but if he holds them because, after &amp;lsquo;careful thought, he finds a balance of evidence in their favor, then his thought is free, however odd his conclusions may seem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freedom from the tyranny of passion is as essential as freedom from the influence of tradition. The lunatic who thinks he is God or the governor of the Bank of England is not a free thinker, because he has allowed the passion of megalomania to get the better of his reason. The jealous husband, who suspects his wife of infidelity on inadequate grounds, and the complacent optimist, who refuses to suspect her when the evidence is overwhelming, are alike permitting passion to enslave their thought; in neither of them is thought free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The freedom that the freethinker seeks is not the absolute freedom of anarchy; it is freedom within the intellectual law. He will not bow to the authority of others, and he will not bow to his own desires, but he will submit to evidence. Prove to him that he is mistaken, and he will change his opinion; supply him with a new fact, and he will if necessary abandon even his most cherished theories. This is not to him a slavery, since his desire is to know, not to indulge in pretty fancies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The desire for knowledge has an element of humility towards facts; in opinion, it submits to the universe. But towards mankind it is not humble; it will not accept as genuine knowledge the counterfeit coin that is too often offered with all the apparatus of authority. The free thinker knows that to control his environment he must understand It, and that the illusion of power to be derived from myths is no better that that of a boastful drunkard. He needs. towards his fellow men, independence; towards his own prejudices, a difficult self-discipline; and towards the world that he wishes to understand a clear untroubled outlook which endeavors to see without distortion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the free thinker, as we have been describing him, a desirable member of society, or is he a menace to all that we ought to hold   sacred? In almost all times and places, he has been held to be a menace, and he is still held to be so, in varying degrees, in almost every country. In Germany he is sent to a concentration camp, in Russia to a Labor Colony in the Arctic; in Japan he is imprisoned for &amp;ldquo;dangerous thoughts&amp;rdquo;; in the United States, though not subject to legal penalties, he is debarred from teaching in the great majority of schools and universities, and has no chance of a political career. Throughout a period of about 1,200 years, every Christian country in Europe condemned free thinkers to be burnt at the stake. In Mohammedan countries, though often protected by monarchs, they were subjects of abhorrence to the mob even in the greatest periods of Arabic and Moorish culture. A hostility so widespread and so nearly universal must have deep roots, partly in human nature, partly in the statecraft of governing cliques; in either case, the soul in which they flourish is fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us consider some of the arguments against free thought that are used by those who are not content with a mere appeal to prejudice. There is first the appeal to modesty, which is used especially by the  old in dealing with rebellious youth. Wise men throughout the ages, it is said, have all been agreed in upholding certain great truths, and who are you to set yourself up against their unanimous testimony? If you are prepared to reject St. Paul and St. Augustine will you be equally contemptuous of Plato and Aristotle? Or, if you despise all the ancients, what about Descartes and Spinoza, Kant and Hegel? Were they not great intellects, who probed matters more deeply than you can hope to do? And is not the pastor of your parents&amp;rsquo; church a virtuous and learned man, who has a degree in theology, and even spent some months in the study of Hebrew? Have you forgotten what Bacon, that good and great man, said about a little knowledge inclining to atheism? Do you pretend that there are no mysteries before which the human intellect is dumb? Pride of intellect is a sin, and you commit it when you set up your own judgment against that of all the wisest men of many centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This argument, expressed in Latin-which is held to make any nonsense respectable-has been erected by the Catholic Church into a first principle: that we cannot err in believing what has been believed always,everywhere, and by everybody. Those who use this argument conveniently forget how many once universal beliefs are now discarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was held that there could not be men at the antipodes, because they would fall off, or at least grow dizzy from standing upside down. Everybody believed that the sun goes round the earth, that there are unicorns, and that toads are poisonous. Until the 16th Century, no one questioned the efficacy of witchcraft; of those who first doubted the truth of this superstition, not a few were burnt at the stake. Who now accepts the doctrine, once almost universal throughout Christendom, that infants who die without being baptized will spend eternity in hell because Adam ate an apple? Yet all these now obsolete doctrines could formerly have been upheld by the appeal to the wisdom of the ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appeal to authority is fallacious, but even so It is questionable whether, if admitted, it would work more in favor of Christianity than against it. I have spent most of my life in the society of authors and men of science; among them, free thought is taken for granted, and the few exceptions are noted as freaks. It is true that most of them have too much worldly wisdom to allow their opinions to beco me known to the orthodox, for even now a known freethinker suf fers various disabilities, and has much more difficulty in making a living than a man who is reputed to accept the teachings of some Church. It is onl y by impos ing this somewhat flimsy hypocrisy that believers are st ill abl e to deceive the young by appealing to authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of anthropology is useful in this respect. Savages at a certain stage of development are found to have very similar beliefs in a ll parts of the world, and to the modern mind these beliefs are almost all absurd . But if mankind continues to advance, we shall, 20.000 years hence, appear to our successors scarcely distinguishable from the savages to whom we feel ourselves so superior. It is custo mary to date anthropological epochs by the materials employed-the stone age , the bronze age, the iron age. But one might equally describe a culture by its prevalent beliefs: the cannibal culture, the animal sacrifice culture, the transubstantiation culture, and so on into the future. See our beliefs as one stage in this development is wholesome. It shows that there is nothing w hich has been believed &amp;ldquo;always, everywhere, and by everybody&amp;rdquo;; and that whatever has been be lieved by everybody in a certain stage of culture has seemed nonsense to everybody in the next stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common body of wisdom to which the conventional and orthodox like to appeal is a myth: there is only the &amp;ldquo;wisdom&amp;rdquo; of one time and place. In every age and in every place, if you wish to be thought well of by influential citizens you must at least seem to share t he ir prejudices, and you must close your mind to the fact that influe nt ia l citizens in other times and places have quite different prej udices. If, on the other hand, you wish to acquire knowledge, you m ust ign ore thein fluential citizens, and rely upon your judgment, even whe n you acceptt he authority of those whom your own judgment pr onounces wort hy of respect. This degree of reliance upon yourself is the first step towards freedom of thought. Not that you need t hi n k yours elf infallible, but that you must learn to think everyone fa llible, an d to content yourself with such greater or less probability as t he eviden ce may seem to you to warrant. This renunciation of absolute certaint y is, to some minds, the most difficult step towards intellectual free dom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the arguments designed to show that free thought is wicked, the one most often used is that without religion people would not be virtuo us. Their virtue. we are told, will fail for two reasons, first, that they will no longer fear personal punishment, and second, t hat they  will no longer know what is virtue and w hat is sin. In usin g this argument, orthodox Catholics have in some ways a logical advantage over Protestants. Let us see how the argument looks from a Catho lic point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theology of sin has always been somewhat intricate, since it has had to face the fundamental question: why did God permit sin?. Augustine held that. from the moment when Adam ate t he a pple,  men h a ve not had free will: they could not. by their own efforts, a bst a in from sin . Since sin deserves punishment, God would have been entirely just if He had condemned the whole human race to h ell. But mercy is also a virtue, and in order to exercise this virtue He had to send another portion of the human race to heaven. Nothing but pure  cap rice, St. Augustine maintained. determined His choice of t he elect and the reprobate. But on the elect. when He had chosen t he m , He bestowed grace. so that they were able, within limits, to a bstain from sin. Th ey were virtuous because they were saved, not saved because they were virtuous. For some obscure reason. grace was never bestowed on the unbaptized&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A certain kindly Welshman named Morgan, who translated his name Into Pelaglus, was a contemporary of St. Augustine, and comhated his doctrine as too severe. Pelagius held that men still have free will, in spite of Adam&amp;rsquo;s sin. He thought it even possible that a human being might be entirely without sin. He thought that the wicked are damned because they sin, whereas st. Augustine thought that they sin because they are damned. Pelagius held that each man had the power to live so virtuously as to deserve heaven, and that his use of his own free will determined the issue between salvation and damnation. St. Augustine&amp;rsquo;s authority secured the condemnation of this doctrine, wnich remained heretical until the Reformation. But at the Reformation Luther and Calvin espoused the theory of predestination with such ardor that the Catholic Church, without formal change, turned increasingly towards the doctrine of Pelagius. This doctrine is now held, in practice if not in theory, not only by the Cathollc Church, but also by the great majority of the Protestants. It has, however, been still further softened by the belief that fewer people go to hell than was formerly thought. Indeed, among Protestants, a complete rejection of hell has become very common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A belief in either hell of purgatory ought, one would suppose, to have a powerful influence in promoting whatever the theologians consider to be virtue. If you accept St. Augustine&amp;rsquo;s doctrine, you will hold that, although it is not virtue that causes you to go to heaven, virtue is a mark of the elect; if you live a sinful life, you will be forced to conclude that you are among the reprobate. You will therefore live virtuously in order to hope that you will go to heaven. If you accept the more usual view that you will be punished hereafter for your sins, either by spending eternity in hell or by a longer or shorter period of purgatorial fires, you will, if you are prudent, consider that, on the balance, the virtuous enjoy more pieasure than the wicked, and that therefore, as a rational hedonist, you had better abstain from sin. If, on the other hand, you do not believe in the life hereafter, you will sin whenever no earthly penalty is to be feared-so at least orthodox theologians seem to think. Whether from introspection or for some other reason, they seem to be all agreed that disinterested virtue is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However that may be, the views of the early Church on sin were found to be too severe for ordinary human nature, and were softened in various ways which, incidentally, increased the power of the priesthood. The sacrament of absolution secures sinners against the extreme penalty of damnation; you may commit all the sins you have a mind to, provided you repent on your deathbed and receive extreme unction. True, you may suffer for a while in purgatory, but your sojourn there can be shortened if masses are said for your soul, and priests will say masses for you if you leave them money for the purpose. Thus the power of wealth extends beyond the grave, and bribery is effective even in heaven. This comfortable doctrine left the rich and powerful free to indulge their passions as they saw fit. In the ages of faith,
murder and rape were far commoner than they have since become. The supposed efficacy of orthodox belief in curbing sin is not borne out by history. Not only have believers been prone to sin, but unbelievers have often been exceptionally virtuous; it would be difficult to point
to any set of men more impeccable than the earnest free thinkers of the 19th Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the champion of orthodoxy will object, when freethinkers are virtuous, it is because they live in a Christian community and have imbibed its ethic in youth; without this influence, they would question the moral law and see no reason to abstain from any infamy. The 0sins of the Nazis and the Bolsheviks are pointed out as the fruits of free thought. But they are not freethinkers according to our definition: they are fanatical adherents of absurd creeds, and their crimes spring from their fanaticism. They are, in fact, the same crimes as those  committed by men like Charles V or Philip II, who were champions of the faith. Charles V, after spending the day conquering a Protestant city, felt that he had earned a little relaxation; he sent his servants out to find a virgin, and they found one of 17. Presumably she got syphilis, but the Emperor got absolution. This is the system which is supposed to preserve men from sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, many who are now universally acknowledged to have been quite exceptionally virtuous incurred obloquy, if not worse, for their opposition to the orthodoxy of their day. Socrates, on the ground that he was guilty of impiety, was condemned to drink the hemlock. Giordano Bruno was burnt by the Inquisition and Servetus was burnt by Calvin, both because, though men of the highest moral excellence, they had fallen into heresy. Spinoza, one of the noblest men known to history, was excommunicated by the Jews and execrated by the Christians; for a hundred years after his death, hardly anyone dared to say a good word for him. The English and American freethinkers of the 18th and early 19th centuries were, for the most part, men of quite exceptional moral excellence; in some cases, such as the Founding Fathers, this is so evident that the orthodox have been driven to conceal the fact that men so universally admired had shocking opinions. In our day free thought still leads men into trouble, but less for attacks on dogma than for criticism of the superstitious parts of religious ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, it is true, some actions labelled &amp;ldquo;sin&amp;rdquo; which are likely to be promoted by free thought. A Jew, when he ceases to be orthodox, may eat pork; a Hindu may commit the offense of eating beef. The Greek Orthodox Church considers it sin for godparents of the same child to marry; I will not deny that free thought may encourage this enormity. Protestants condemn amusements on Sunday, and Catholics condemn birth control; in these respects, also, free thought may be inimical to what bigots choose to call virtue. Moral codes which are irrational, and have no basis except in superstition, cannot long survive the habit of disinterested thinking. But if a moral code seems to promote human well-being in this terrestrial existence, it has no need of supernatural sanctions. Kindliness and intelligence are the chief sources of useful behavior, and neither is promoted by causing people to believe, against all reason, in a capricious and vindictive deity who practices a degree of cruelty which, in the strictest mathematic sense, surpasses infinitely that of the worst human beings who have ever existed. Modern liberal Christians may protest that this is not the sort of God in whom they believe, but they should realize that only the teachings of persecuted freethinkers have caused this moral advance in their beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come now to another class of arguments against free thought, namely those which may be called political. In former times, these arguments took a very crude form : it is all very well (it was said) for the rich and powerful to be skeptics, but the poor need some theological belief to make them contented with their lot . If they can be induced to think that this life of tribulation is only a brief prelude to eternal bliss, and that rewards in heaven are much more likely to go to the poor than to the rrcfi, they will be less inclined to listen to subversive propaganda, particularly if heaven is only to be the reward of the submissive. This point of view existed in antiquity and throughout the Middle Ages, but it was especially prevalent in the early 19th Century, when the preaehing of Methodism induced acquiescence among the victims of the atrocious industrial system of that period. This frank defense of earthly injustice as a preface to celestial justice has now been pretty generally abandoned, but not, for the most part, through the initiative of champions of religion. It was mainly men like Tum Paine, Robert Owen, and Karl Marx, freethinkers all, who shamed the orthodox rich out of this complacent attempt to interpret L~od as the Supreme Capitalist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, however, a generalized form of the same argument, which deserves more respect, and calls for serious discussion. In this form, the argument maintains that social cohesion, without which no community can survive, is only rendered possible by some unifying creed or moral code, and that no such creed or code can long survive the corrosive effect of skeptical criticism. There have been periods so it is alleged when denial of traditional orthodoxies caused political disaster; of these the most notable are the great age of Greece and the epoch of the Italian Renaissance. It is customary among the ignorant to bring up the fall of Rome in this connection, and to link it with the wickedness of Nero. But as the fall of Rome did not occur until 400 years after the time of Nero, and as meanwhile the Romans had undergone a great moral purification, culminating in the adoption of Christianity, this example is ill chosen. The other two deserve more serious discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greek cities lost their independence, first to the Macedonians, and then, more completely, to the Romans, and this loss occurred at a time when the ancient pieties had been dissolved by free inquiry. But there is no reason to connect their fall with their skepticism. They fell because they could not unite, and their failure to unite was due to ordinary political causes, such as, in our own day, prevented the smaller neutrals from uniting against Hitler. No intensity of religious belief could have saved them; only a rare degree of political sagacity would have been of any service. Carthage fell equally, though at the crisis the Carthaginians sacrificed their children to Moloch as religiously as any champion of religion could wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much the same considerations apply to Italy in the renaissance. France and Spain were Great Powers, to which the small Italian States could offer no effective opposition. In the face of traditional enmities unity was difficult, as it always is in such circumstances; its most fOlceful advocate was the wicked Machiavelli, and, as he points out, its most powerful opponent was the Pope. No serious historical student can maintain that the enslavement of Italy was due to lack of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may however concede one thing to those who urge that religion is socially necessary. Where the Church has been a very powerful organization, and has played a great part in regulating men&amp;rsquo;s lives, sudden dissolution may leave them without the accustomed external guidance, and render society somewhat chaotic until new organizations grow up. But in this respect the Church is no different from any other important organization. Social cohesion is important, and the Church has been one of the ways of securing it, but there are innumerable other ways which do not demand so high a price in mental bondage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some men argue that the question whether rellgious dogmas are true or false is unimportant; the important thing, they say, is that these beliefs are comforting. How could we face life, they ask, if this world were all, and if we had no assurance that its apparent evil serves some great purpose? Will not belief in immortality promote courage in the face of death? Will not the belief that the course of history is ordarned by an all-wise beneficent Providence help us to stand firm in times when evil appears to be triumphant? Why rob ourselves or others of this source of happiness by listening to the dubious arguments of those who refuse to believe in anything that cannot be demonstrated by the cold intellect? Has not the heart its rights? Why should it submit to the head? As the poet Tennyson exclaims in rebutting the contentions of skeptics: Like a man in wrath the heart, Stood up and answered: I have felt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is to my mind something pusillanimous and sniveling about this point of view, which makes me scarcely able to consider it with patience. To refuse to face facts merely because they are unpleasant is considered the mark of a weak character, except in the sphere of religion. I do not see how it can be ignoble to yield to the tyranny of fear in all ordinary terrestrial matters, but noble and virtuous to do exactly the same thing when God and the future life are concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the defenders of orthodoxy may argue, you do not know that religious beliefs are untrue. Where all is doubtful, why not accept the more cheerful alternative? This is the argument of William James&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Will to Believe,&amp;rdquo; The duty of veracity, he says, has two parts: first,
to believe what is true; second, to disbelieve what is false. To these two parts he attaches equal authority. The skeptic, who suspends judgment in the absence of adequate evidence, is certainly failing to believe what is true, whereas, if he adopted either alternative, he might
be succeeding in believing what is true. On this ground, in the name of veracity, William James condemns the skeptic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His argument, however, is shockingly sophistical. The virtue of veracity does not consist in believing all sorts of things at a venture, on the off chance that they may happen to be true. No one would for a moment take this point of view except as regards religion. Suppose I get into conversation with a stranger, am I to believe that his name is Wilkinson on the ground that, if it is, I shall be believing truly, whereas if I admit that I do not yet know his name I forfeit the chance of a true belief? You will say that there are known to be many surnames, and therefore each is improbable. But there are also many rereligions. If I am to believe at a venture, shall I believe what I am told by the Buddhists, or the Hindus, or the Christians? And if I choose the Christians, shall I prefer the Catholics, or the Lutherans, or the Calvinists, or the Muggletonians, or the Particular Baptists? On William James&amp;rsquo; principle I ought to believe them all, so as to have the greatest possible chance of believing something true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inconclusive character of the arguments against this or that theological dogma, even when fully admitted, does not justify belief in anyone of the mutually inconsistent systems that human fantasy has created. I cannot prove that the Hindus are mistaken in attributing a peculiar sacredness to the cow, or that the Mohammendans are wrong in thinking that only the followers of the Prophet will enjoy the delights of paradise. Perhaps Mr. Muggleton was as great a man as the Muggletonians contend; perhaps the Seventh Day Adventists are right in thinking that it is on Saturdays that God wants us to do no work. But if we are going to adopt all these beliefs, as William James&amp;rsquo;s princlples would lead us to do, we shall find life somewhat difficult. We must not eat beef because the Hindus may be right, or pork because the Jews may be right, or beans because Pythagoras forbad them. We must not work on Fridays, Saturdays, or Sundays, to obey Mohammedan, Jewish and Christian precepts; the remaining days will mostly be sacred days in some religion. Perhaps in the end a general skepticism may seem less inconvenient than the consolations of all the religions at once. But how is a fair-minded man to choose among them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The virtue of veracity, as I conceive it, consists in giving to every suggested belief the degree of credence that the evidence warrants. We give whole-hearted credence to our perceptions, almost compiete credence to what is well-established in science, such as predic-
tions of eclipses, but much less to what is still somewhat tentative, such as the weather forecast. We do not doubt that there was a famous man called Julius Caesar, but about Zoroaster we are not so sure. Veracity does not consist simply In believing or disbelieving, but also in suspending judgment, and in thinking some things probable and others improbable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, says William James, you must, in any doubtful situation, act either on belief or disbelief, and whichever you act upon the other alternative is practically rejected. This is an undue simplification. Many hypotheses are worth acting upon in certain ways, but not in others. If I am healthy, I may act upon the hypothesis that the weather is going to be fine, but if I have a peculiar sensibility to chills I may require very strong evidence before it becomes wise to adopt this hypothesis. I may act upon the hypothesis that only the good can go to heaven to the extent of being good myself, without being justified in acting on it to the extent of burning those whom I think not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all obliged constantly to act upon doubtful hypotheses, but when we do so we ought to take care that the results will not be very disastrous if the hypotheses are false. And when we act upon a doubtful hypothesis, we ought not to persuade ourselves that it is certain, for then we close our minds against new evidence, and also venture on actions (such as persecution) which are very undesirable if the hypothesis is false. And for this reason praise and blame ought not to be attached to beliefs or disbeliefs, but only to rational or irrational ways of holding them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of free thought is the same thing as the importance of veracity. Veracity does not necessarily consist in believing what is in fact true, because sometimes the available evidence may point to a wrong conclusion. Occasions may arise when the most conscientiousjury will condemn a man who is in fact innocent, because unfortunate circumstances have made him seem guilty. Te be always right is not possible for human beings, but it is possible always to try to be right. Veracity consists in trying to be right in matters of belief, and also in doing what is possible to insure that others are right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should veracity be regarded as important? The reasons are partly personal, partly social. Let us begin with the social reasons. Every powerful individual or group depends upon the existence of certain beliefs in others. The Dalai Lama is powerful in Tibet, the Caliph used to be powerful in the Muslim world, the Pope is powerful among Catholics, and the power of these men depends upon the belief of their followers that they have some peculiar holiness. The Dalai Lama makes (or made) large sums of money by selling pills made out of his excrement. What the Caliph used to make out of being holy is familiar to every reader of the Arabian Nights. The Pope has been shorn of some of his glory by the wickedness of Protestants and freethinkers, but in the great days of the Italian renaissance he enjoyed immense splendor. Is it to be supposed that men in such a position will encourage a rational examination of their claims? The Dalai Lama, like the vendors of patent medicines among ourselves. would obviously stick at nothing to prevent a scientific investigation of the efficacy various pills, or at any rate to prevent its results from becoming known. He may himself, like some of the Renaissance Popes, be completely skeptical, but he will not wish his disciples to resemble him in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever there is power, there is a temptation to encourage irrational credulity in those who are subject to the power in question. Kings have been supposed to be sacred beings; the Mikado is still a divinity descended from the sun-goddess. Sometimes the business of sacredness is overdone. The king of Dahomey had such majesty that whenever he looked towards any part of his dominions tempests arose in that part; he therefore had to look always at the ground, which made him easy to assassinate. But when the king as an individual is hampered in this way, certain people in his entourage can use his magical powers for their own ends, so that there is no gain to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When superstition is needed to promote tyranny, free thought is likely to cause revolution. But when the population has been accustomed to irrational reverence, it is likely to transfer its reverence to the leader of a successful revolution. Ikons are still habitual in Russia,
but of Lenin or Stalin instead of Our Lady. The chief gain in such a case is that the new superstition is not likely to have such a firm hold as the old one had; Stalin-worship could be upset by a less terrific upheval than the revolution of 1917.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a population is to escape tyranny, it must have a freethinking attitude towards its government and the theories upon which its government is based, that is to say, it must demand that the government shall act in the general interest, and must not be deceived by a superstitious theology into the belief that what is in fact only the interest of the governing clique is identical with the general interest. For obedience to a tolerable government there are abundant rational motives, but when obedience is given for irrational reasons the resulting &amp;ldquo;lavishness encourages the government to become tyrannical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the Reformation, the State has increasingly replaced the Church as the object of superstitious reverenece. At first, the State was embodied in the King: Henry VIII in England and Louis XIV in France were able to do abominable things because of the divinity that does hedge a king. But in Germany and Russia it has been found possible, by means of a fanatical creed, to generate a similar feeling of awe towards a revolutionary leader, and in order to achieve this end free thought has been suppressed more vigorously than at any time since the 17th Century. Only a general growth of free thought can, in the long run, save these countries from a self-imposed despotism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of control over opinion to promote the power of a dominant class is best shown in the growth of Catholic theology. The power of the priesthood depends upon its ability to decide whether you shall go to heaven or to hell, and, in the former event, how long you shall spend in purgatory. What must you do in order to be among the fortunate? Must you lead a virtuous life? Must you love your neighbor, as Christ ordained? Or must you obey the still more difficult precept to sell all you have and give to the poor? No, you need do none of these things. Getting to heaven is a matter of red tape, like getting to a foreign country in war time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you must avoid heresy, that is to say, you must believe
everything that the Church tells you to believe. You need not know what the dogmas of the Church are, because that is difficult except for educated theologians, but you must hold no opinions contrary to these dogmas, and, if you ever feel tempted to do so, you must abandon the dangerous opinions as soon as you are officially informed that
they are not orthodox. In a word, on all the most important subjects you must never think for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As regards conduct, you need not avoid sin; indeed, it is heretical to suppose that you can. You are sure to sin, but that need not trouble you provided you take the proper steps. There are seven deadly sins; if you commit any of these, and die before taking the proper steps, you
will go to hell, but all can be forgiven to those who go through the correct routine. You must first tell some priest all about it. and profess due penitence. He can then absolve you, but may impose a penance as the condition of absolution. You are now safe from hell, so far as
that particular sin is concerned, but to shorten your time in purgatory there are various things that it is wise to do, most of which increase either the power or the income of the priesthood. If you have enough money, you can commit a great many sins and nevertheless get to heaven pretty soon. The more sins you commit, the more the Church profits by the steps you have to take to mitigate the punishment. The system is convenient both for priests and for sinners, but it is preposterous to pretend that it promotes virtue. What it does promote is men t al docility and abject fear .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not wish to suggest that these defects are peculiarly characteristic of the Catholic Church. They exist equally under the tyranny of the Nazi party and the Communist party. The sins to which these parties object are somewhat different from those to which the Church
objects: in particular, they are less obsessed by sex. And the punishment of sin, under their regime, is in this world, not in the next. But otherwise there is much similarity, except for the differences that must exist between what is new and what is old and tried and established.
What is in common is the power of one group, based on irrational beliefs. And the ultimate cure, in all these forms of mental tyranny, is freedom of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is odd that the orthodox, while decrying free thought in their own day, are quite willing to admit a host of truths which would never have become known but for the freethinkers of earlier ages. It was freethinkers in early Greece who persuaded their compatriots, in spite of the opposition of the priests of Delphi, to abandon the practice of human sacrifice. Anaxagoras, who taught that the sun and moon are not gods, only escaped death for impiety by flight from Athens. Those who disbelieved in witchcraft were told, quite truly, that to question witchcraft is to question the Bible. Galileo, for holding that the earth goes round the sun, was forced under threat of torture to recant, was kept in prison, and was ordered to repeat daily the seven penitential psalms to show his contrition for having used his mind. Darwin, fortunately for himself, lived in an age when persecution was in abeyance, but he was denounced by the orthodox, and they would have suppressed his teaching if they had had the power. Every intellectual advance, and a great many moral reforms, have had to fight for Victory against the forces of obscurantism. Nevertheless, in what the obscurantists still defend, they are as obstinate as they ever were. Progress, pow as in the past, is only possible in the teeth of their bitter hostlllty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The personal and private reasons in favor of veracity in thinking are no less cogent than the public reasons. We all know the kind of person who cannot bear any unpalatable fact, and we know that, to those who live with them, they appear irritating and contemptible. In Shakespeare&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Antony and Cleopatra&amp;rdquo; Cleopatra orders the messenger who brings news of Antony&amp;rsquo;s marriage to Octavia to be scourged. After this, people are wary of telling her anything that may annoy her, and, hugging her illusions, she goes straight to disaster. In regard to mundane affairs, the capacity to assimilate what is unpleasant is a condition of success, and for this reason, if for no other, it is a mistake to wrap oneself around with comfortable fairytales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it will be said, beliefs about the next world are in quite a diferent category. However false they may be, they will not be refuted by any experience during this life. Even if there is no such place as heaven, the man who expects to go there will have a happier life than
the man who regards death as annihiliatlon. What advantage is there, then, in thinking truly about such a matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to begin with, veracity consists, as we havc already said, not in having true beliefs, but in trying to have them. The man who, after a dispassionate examination of the evidence, has decided that there is a future life, is not lacking in veracity; this lack exists only in the believer who refuses to examine the evidence because he fcars that it may prove inadequate. This man is like one who refuses to open a letter because it may contain bad news. When a man allows one kind of fear to dominate him, he soon comes to be dominated by other kinds also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world in which we live is full of unpleasant things, some of which are pretty sure to happen to ourselves. If we are to preserve self-respect, and to merit the respect of others, we must learn to endure such things, not only when they happen, but in prospect. The man who fears that there is no evidence for immortality, but nevertheless clings to the belief by closing his mind, is no better than a man who fears he has cancer, but refuses a medical examinatton lest his fears should be confirmed. Each alike is on a level with the soldier who runs away in battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the worst aspects of orthodox Christianity Is that it sanctifies fear, both personal and impersonal. Fear of hell, fear of extinction, fear lest the universe should be purposeless, are regarded as noble emotions, and men who allow themselves to be dominated by such fears are thought superior to men who face what is painful without flinching. But human nature cannot be so completely departmentalized that fear can be exalted in one direction without acquiring a hold in other directions also. The man who thinks himself virtuous in fearing an angry God will soon begin to see virtue in submission to earthly tyrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the best character there is an element of pridenot the sort of pride that despises others, but the sort that will not be deflected from what it thinks good by outside pressure. The man who has this sort of pride will wish, as far as may be, to know the truth about matters that concern him, and will feel himself a slave if, in his thought, he yields to fear. But this kind of pride is condemned by the Church as a sin, and is called &amp;ldquo;pride of intellect.&amp;rdquo; For my part, so far from regarding it as a sin, I hold is to bc one of the greatest and most desirable of virtues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is time to tackle the more specific questions: Is there evidence in favor of Christian dogmas, either in the old rigid forms or in the vaguer forms favored by modernists? And, if there is not such evidence, is there nevertheless reason to think that belief in Christian dogmas does good?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old orthodoxy has now fallen into almost universal disfavor, even among Catholics. Catholics still believe in hell, but by means of the doctrine of invincible Ignorance they escape the necessity of believing that their Protestant friends will go there. Indeed there is hardly anybody they know to be damned, except Judas Iscariot. Nevertheless, they are still, theoretically, in favor of persecution, of which the justification was that heresy leads to damnation. In this as in various other respects, Catholic ethics has not yet drawn all the inferences that follow from the liberalizing of Catholic theology. Perhaps in time these inferences will be drawn. But as in purely theological matters, the driving force will have to come from freethinkers. But for their influence, Catholic theology would still be as rigid as in the middle ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we may say that what is essential to Christianity as conceived by modern theologians is belief in God and immortality, together with a moral code which is more traditional than that of most freethinkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What reasons are there for belief in God? In old days, there were a variety of purely intellectual arguments, which were thought to make it irrational to doubt the existence of God. The chief of these was the argument of the First Cause: in tracing events backward from effects to causes, we must, it was thought, come to an end somewhere, since an infinite series is impossible. Wherever we come to an end, we have reached a Cause which is not an effect, and this Cause is God. This and other purely intellectual arguments were criticized by freethinkers, and in the end most theologians came to admit that they are invalid. The argumen ts upon which most modern theologians rely are less precise and more concerned with moral issues. In the main, they result from examination of what is called the religious consciousness or the religious experience. I do not think they are any more cogent than the old arguments, but because of their vagueness they are less susceptible to precise refutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are told that we have a moral sense which must have had supernatural origin. We are told also that certain people have religious experiences in which they become aware of God with the same certainty with which we become aware of tables and chairs. It is thought to be irrational to question this evidence merely on the ground that only certain people have the mystical experiences in question. We accept a host of things in science on the word of certain skilled observers; why not accept things in religion on the word of the skilled observers in this field?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the mystic, who is persuaded that he himself has seen God, it is useless to argue about the matter. If he has moments when he IS amenable to reason, one may point out that innumerable people have seen Satan, in whom most modern mystics do not believe. We may point out that Mr. so and so, who is a devotee of the worship of Bacchus, has seen pink rats. but has not been able to persuade other zoologists of their reality. We may trace the history of visions and hallucinations, pointing out how they are colored by the previous beliefs of the seers or lunatics concerned. St. Anthony in the desert was constantly troubled by apparitions of naked ladies; are we to infer that the Koran is right in promising abundance of such sights in Paradise? Perish the thought!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such things, I say, we may point out, but probably in vain. A lady of my acquaintance took to fasting, and recommended the practice on the ground that it gave rise to visions. &amp;ldquo;Yes,&amp;rdquo; I said, &amp;ldquo;if you drink too much you see snakes, and if you eat too little you see angels.&amp;rdquo; But, alas! she was only annoyed. She held, as many mystics do, that a vision must be veridical if it is edifying and results from virtuous living. This view is only justified if we already know that the world is governed by a beneficent Providence which rewards those who obey Its laws by allowing them glimpses of the felicity to come. What if, as some heretics have thought, this wo d is the empire of Satan, who rewards the wicked not only with riches and power, but with hidden magical lore? In that case, the visions of the wicked wili deserve more credence than those of the good, and we shall listen with more respect to the revelations of the drunkard than to those of the ascetic. Before we can decide, therefore, what weight to attach to the testimony of the mystics, we must first inquire whether there are any grounds for believing in a good God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;God, In orthodox theology, is the omnipotent Creator, who made the world out of nothing. There are some liberal theologians nowadays who deny His omnipotence; I shall consider their view presently, but first let us examine the more usual and correct opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view has been most clearly and exactly expressed by the philosopher Leibniz. According to him. God, before creating the world, surveyed all the worlds that are logically possible, and compared them as the amount of good and evil that they severally contained. Being beneficent, He decided to create that one of the possible worlds that  contained the greatest excess of good over evil. This world happened  to contain a good deal of evil, but the evil was logically bound up with  t.ne greater good. In particular, sin Is an evil, but free will is a good. Not even omnipotence can confer free wili without the possibilty of sin, but free wili is so great a good that God decided to create a world containing both free wili and sin rather than a world containing neither. He did so, and Adam ate the apple. Hence all our sorrows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty fable. and I will not deny that it is logically possible, but that is the utmost that I wili concede. It is exactly equally possible that the world was created by a wholly malicious devil, who allowed a certain amount of good in order to increase the sum of evil. Let us suppose his ethical valuations to be entirely orthodox, but his wili to be towards what Is bad. &amp;ldquo;He would agree with the theologians In thinking sin the greatest of evils, and would perceive that sin is impossible without free will. He would therefore create things possessed of free will, in spite of the fact that free wili made virtue possible. He would be consoled, however, by the foreknowledge that virtue would be very rare. And so this actual world, which he created, is the worst of all possible worlds, although it contains some things that are good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not advocating this fable, any more than Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s. Both seem to me to be equally fantastic. The only difference betwen them I. that one is pleasant, the other unpleasant, but this difference has sufficed to make Christians accept the one and rej ect the other. No one asked: Why should the truth be pleasant? What reason have we to think our wishes a key to reality? the only rational answer is: None whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shifts to which theologians have been put to prove the world such as a good God could have created are sometimes very curious. In 1755 there was a great earthquake in Lisbon, which shook Voltaire&amp;rsquo;s faith. But Rousseau pointed out that the loss of life was due to people living in high houses; if they had run wild in the woods, like the noble savage, they would not have suffered; they were therefore justly punished for their sins. Bernard Bosanquet, the leading British philosopher of my youth, went so far as to argue that, on purely logical grounds, earthquakes. though possible in second-rate capitals such as Lisbon, could not occur in a really great city like London. The Tokyo earthquake occurred after his book was published, but then the Japanese, as we know, are wicked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 18th Century it was held that all suffering, even that of animals, is due to Adam&amp;rsquo;s sin, and did not exist before the fall. Until that fatal moment, mosquitoes did not sting, snakes were not venomous, and lions were strictly vegetarian. Unfortunately, in the early 19th Century geologists discovered fossils of carnivorous animals which, it. was rightly held, must have existed before man appeared on the earth. We can all see how right and just it is that animals eaten by other animals should suffer because Adam and Eve were wicked, but why should they have suffered before our parents first sinned? This problem caused agonies of perplexity to the pious biologists of a hundred years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some forms of punishment here on earth are specially reserved for sinners. Persecutors of the early Church, as Lactantius pointed out, were apt to be eaten of worms. The death of Artus, who held shocking opinions on the Trinity, was a warning to sinners: his bowels gushed out, as did those of some less famous heretics. But Montaigne pointed out that the same fate had befallen men of undoubted virtue; it only remained, therefore, to fall back on the mysterious dispensations of Providence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The favorite argument was, and perhaps still is, the argument from design. Could this universe, obedient as it is to natural laws, have come about without a Lawgiver? Could the sublimity of the starry heavens, the majesty of the ocean, the song of the skylark, and the
loveliness of spring flowers, have come about by chance? As the poet sings: Behold the snowflake exquisite in form, Was it made perfect by unwilling norm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument from design has, however, a logical weakness when used by those who believe the Creator to be omnipotent. Design implies the necessity of using means, which does not exist for omnipotence. When we desire a house, we have to go through the labor of building it, put Aladdin&amp;rsquo;s genie could cause a palace to exist by magic. The long process of evolution might be necessary to a divine Artificer who found matter already in existence, and had to struggle to bring order out of chaos. But to the God of Genesis and of orthodox theology no such laborious process was needed; no gradual process, no adaptation of means to ends, was required by the Being could say: Let there be light, and there was light. The vast astronomical and geological ages before life existed may have been inevitable for a finite Deity working in a reluctant material, but for Omnipotence they would have been a gratuitous waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us then consider the hypothesis (which now has influential advocates) of a God who is not omnipotent, who is well meaning, but has constantly to struggle against obstacles put in his way by preexisting Nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hypothesis, it must be said, cannot be disproved. There is nothing known about the universe that proves it to be false. But it is open to the same objection that we formerly used against Lelbniz, that is to say, that a non-omnipotent devil is as least as plausible as
a non-omnipotent God. On this hypothesis, we shall suppose that the universe originally consisted only of matter, with the sole exception of Satan, who studied it scientifically with a view to discovering its potentialities of evil. He soon saw that there could be no evil
without life, and he therefore set to work to discover how to create life. He had to wait a long time, till the nebula had condensed into stars ,the stars had thrown out planets, and the planets had cooled. At last, when the moment had arrived so far as physics was concerned,
he set to work to study chemistry, and discovered that a certain compound, if he could synthesize it, would be at once sentient and self-perpetuating. After many efforts, he succeded in making the germ of life; then, with the sense of labor rewarded, he mumbled: Mischief, thou are afoot! Now let it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first the process was regrettably slow. Sea slime had only the rudiments of feeling, and even when evolution had got as far as oysters their pangs were still regrettably dim. But after that things began to go better. Sharks kept humbler .fishes in a state of terror,
hawks made little birds miserable, and cats brought tragedy into the lives of mice. But there was still something lacking: in between times, animals would persist in being happy, and forgetting the horrors that the next moment might bring At last, to Satan&amp;rsquo;s infinite delight, Man was evolved, with the fatal gifts of memory and foresight. Each horror that happened to Man left its indelible mark in his mind; he could not forget that what had occurred might occur again, and in warding off misfortune he lost the joy of life. Furious at his own misery, he sought the cause in the misdeeds of other men, and turned upon them in savage battle, thus magnifying a thousand times the ills that Nature has provided. With increasing glee, Satan watched the dismal process. At last, to crown his joy, men appeared who suffered not only from
their own suffering, but from that of all mankind. Their preaching roused their followers to anger against those who refused to accept it, and so in the end increased the sum of human misery. When Satan saw this, his happiness was at last complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all this is nothing but a pleasant fancy. Men, as is natural, have an intense desire to humanize the universe: God and Satan, alike, are essentially human figures, the one a projection of ourselves, the other of our enemies. Both alike have purposes, and their activities, like ours, spring from desire. A somewhat difficult effort of imagination is required before we can conceive a universe without purpose, developing blindly in accordance with aimless habits. We feel an impulse to ask why? meaning not from what causes, but to what end. The Greeks thought that the sun and moon and planets were each moved about by a god, who was actuated by an :esthetic love of regularity such as inspired the Parthenon. This view made the heavens feel cozy. But gradually it was discovered that the regularity is only approximate: the planets move in ellipses, not in circles, and even the ellipses are inaccurate. The only thing that seemed to remain precise and exact was Newton&amp;rsquo;s law of gravitation, though now we know that this too was only roughly true. However, there certainly seemed to be laws of nature, and where there are laws (we are told) there must be a Lawgiver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the period immediately following Newton this point of view had much plausibility, and convinced even such temperamental skeptics as Voltaire. But alas! The laws of nature are not what they used to be; they have become mere statistical averages. There is no longer anything in physics to suggest the Almighty Watchmaker, who made such a superlative watch that it only had to be wound up once. The laws of nature, like the laws of chance, are only verified when large numbers of Instances arc concerned, and then only approximately. Moreover, the universe, like humanly made watches, and unlike the superlative watch of 18th Century theology, is running down; energy Is only useful when it is unevenly distributed, and it is continually ap proaching nearer and nearer to complete equality of distribution. When once this perfection of cosmic democracy has been achieved, nothing of the slightest interest to man or God or devil can ever happen again, unless omnipotence sees fit to wind the watch up once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after all, the champion of cosmic purpose will say, it is Life that exhibits the important part of the divine plan; the rest is only  stage scenery. Before Darwin, the marvellous adaptation of animals  to their environment was regarded as evidence of benevolent purpose on the part of the Deity, but the theory of natural selection provided a scientific explanation of a vast collection of facts which had been &amp;lsquo;serviceable to the theologians. We can now see, in a general way, how, given the chemical properties of living substance, ordinary physical  and chemical forces were likely to set the process of evolution in motion. True. we cannot manufacture life in the laboratory, and until we have done so it is open to the orthodox to maintain that we shall never be able to do so. But for my part I see no reason why organic chemists could not, within the next hundred years, manufacture living micro-organisms. It may take some time-say a milllon years to cause these to develop by artificial selection into giraffes and hippopotamuses and tigers. When this has been achieved, no doubt the theologians will still maintain that MAN can only be made by the Deity, but I fear the biologists will soon refute this last hope. Whether artificial man will be better or worse than the natural sort I do not venture to predict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There would seem, therefore, to be no evidence that the course of events has been planned either by an omnipotent or by a non-omnipotent Deity: there is also no evidence that it has not been planned. Nor, if there be a Deity, is there any evidence as to his moral attributes. He may be doing His best under difflculties; He may be doing His worst, but be unable to prevent the accidental emergence of a little bit of good now and then. Or, again, His purposes may be purely resthctic: He may not care whether His creatures are happy or unhappy, but only whether they provide a pleasing spectacle. All these hypotheses are equally probable, in the sense that there is not a shred of evidence for or against any of them. Nor should we neglect the Zoroastrian hypothesis of two Great Spirits, one good and one bad, the good one to achieve final victory when Persia conquers all the world. Arlstotle thought there were 47 or 55 gods; this view also deserves our charitable respect. Of possible hypotheses there is no end, but in the a bsence of evidence we have no right to incline towards those that we happen to find agreeable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we to think of immortality? To most modern Christians this question seems to be bound up with that of the existence of God, but both historically and logically the questions are quite distinct. Buddhists. though in their early days they were Atheists, believed that the soul survives death, except when such a pitch of virtue has been achieved as to deserve Nirvana. The Jews of the Old Testament, though they believed in God, did not (for the most part) believe in immortality. Clearly both these views are possible; the question of immortality is therefore, at least in some degree, distinct from that of the existence of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the natural theology that has grown up in Christian civlllzations, the two questions are connected through Divine Justice. The good, in this life, are not always happy, nor are the wicked always unhappy, Therefore, if the world is governed by a just God, there must be a future life, where the good will enjoy eternal bliss and the wicked will suffer eternal torment at any rate such purifying pains as may ultimately make them good. If there is a just God, and if there is free will (without which sin becomes meaningless), there is some force In this argument. Are there any others that should convince us of the Immortality of the soul?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, what is meant by &amp;ldquo;the soul&amp;rdquo;? We are supposed to consist of two things, one called a body, the other called the mind or soul. The body can be weighed on a weighing machine, it can move about, fall downstairs, have pieces cut off by a surgeon, and so on. The mind, meanwhile, does quite other things: it thinks and feels and wills. If my leg is amputated, no part of my soul is cut off; conversely, when I sleep my body remains intact. Among the movements of my body, we can distinguish those that spring from the mind from those that have a purely physical origin: if I walk along a street, I do so because my mind has so chosen, but if I slip on a piece of orange peel my mind has no part in causing the consequent collapse. These distinctions are so familiar that we take them as a matter of course, but their origin is in fact theological rather than scientific. They begin with Plato, so Jar as explicit philosophy is concerned, but were taken over by him from the Orphic religion. From Plato, and also from some other sources, the separation of soul and body was taken over by Christianity, and in time people came to think of it as an unquestionable truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in fact both soul and body are metaphysical abstractions; what we know from experience are occurrences. We know thoughts, but not the supposed thinker; we know particular volitions, but not the will per se. Nor are we In any better case as regards the body. Physicists, who are supposed to know most about matter, say the oddest things about it. According to them, it is merely a convenient fiction; what really goes on In the physical world, they say, is a perpetual redistribution of energy, sometimes by sudden explosions, sometimes In gradually spreading waves. The body, which seems so solid and familiar, consists, they say, mainly of holes in waves of probability. If you do not understand what this means, I will confess that I do not either. But however that may be, it is clear that my body, which Is described on my passport, and my mind, which is described by other philosophers, are alike mainly convenient ways of grouping phenomena, and that phenomena, so far as we know them, have not the characteristics that we associate either with mind or with body, since they are brief and evanescent. The phenomena, in fact, are not specially mental or specially material; they are the raw material out of which, for convenience of discourse, we construct the systems that we call minds and bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of the immortality of the soul can, however, be restated so as to take account of these modern theories, Our thoughts and feelings, while we live, are linked together by memory and experience. We can Inquire whether, after we are dead, there will still be thoughts and feelings that remember those we had when we lived on earth, for, if there will be, they may be regarded as still belonging to us, in the only sense in which our thoughts and feelings in this life belong to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stated in this way, it must be said that immortality appears exceedingly improbable. Memory is clearly associated with the brain, and there is nothing to suggest that memory can survive after the brain has disintegrated. This seems as improbable as that a fire will survive atter it has burnt everything combustible in its neighborhood. It would be going too far to say that we know such things to be impossible; we seldom know enough to say that this or that cannot happen. But on ordinary scientific grounds, seeing the intimate correlation of mental and cerebral organization, we can say that the survival of the one without the other must remain no more than a bare possibility. with much evidence against it and none in its favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, even supposing the dogmas of religion to be false. it may be urged that they afford comfort to believers and do little harm. That they do little harm Is not true. Opposition to birth control makes it impossible to solve the population problem, and therefore postpones
Indefinitely all chance of world peace; it also secures. wherever the Jaw is what the Catholic vote has made it in Connecticut. that women incapable of surviving childbirth shall die in futile confinements. The influence of the Anglican Church in England suffices to insure that
victims of cancer shall suffer agonies as long as possible, however much they themselves may desire euthanasia. Orthodox Protestantism in Tennessee suffices to prevent honest teaching of biology. Not only. however, where the law Intervenes does orthodoxy do harm. I was myself at one time officially concerned in the appointment of a philosophy professor in an important American university; all the others agreed that of course he must be a good Christian. Practically all philosophers of any intellectual eminence are openly or secretly freethinkers; the insistence on orthodoxy therefore necessitated the appointment of a nonenity or a humbug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On many important moral issues of modern times, the Church has thrown Its Influence on the side of cruelty or illegality. I will give two examples. Leopold, King of the Belgians. was also King of the Congo &amp;ldquo;Free&amp;rdquo; State. His rule involved what were probably the worst
and most systematic atrocities in the long blood-stained annals of the oppression of Negroes by white men. When the facts became known. the Belgian Socialist Party. which consisted of free-thinkers, did everything in Its power to mitigate the horrors of the King&amp;rsquo;s personal tyranny; the Church, on the contrary, was obstructive and tried in every possible way to Interefere with the publicity of those who were denouncing the horrors. The Church failed. but if the natives of the Belgian Congo no longer suffer as they did it is no thanks to the professed followers of Christ who occupied the important posts in the Catholic hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other example is more recent. It is supposed that we are fighting to secure the reign of law and the victory of democracy. Spain had a legally elected democratic government, but the Church disliked It. Pious Generals who were orthodox sons of the Church made a military insurrection against the legal and democratic government. and in the end the Church, with the help of Hitler and Mussolini, was successful in reimposing tyranny on the gallant Spanish champions of freedom. In this contest America officially refused to 11ft a finger  to help the Loyalists. and even strained the interpretation of the law  so as to prevent help from being given to the Loyalists by private  American citizens. The government took this line in order to please American Catholics. with the result, not only that the Spaniards suffer, but that we have lost a possible ally in the war. The British government. perhaps for somewhat dille; .u reasons. was at least equally culpable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christian orthodoxy. however, is no longer the chief danger to free thought. The greatest danger in our day comes from new religions. Communism and Nazism. To call these religions may perhaps be objectionable both to their friends and to their enemies, but in fact they
have all the characteristics of religions. They advocate a way of life on the basis of irrational dogmas; they have a sacred history, a Messiah, and a priesthood. I do not see what more could be demanded to qualify a doctrine as a religion. But let us examine each of them
Po little more narrowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I speak of communism in this connection, I do not mean the doctrine that men&amp;rsquo;s goods ought to be held in common. This is an ancient doctrine, advocated by Plato, apparently held by the primitive Church, revived constantly by religious sects during the middle
ages, and condemned by one of the 39 Articles of the Church of England. With its truth or falsehood I am not concerned; what I am concerned with is the doctrine of the modern Communistic Party, and of the Russian Government to which it owes allegiance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to this doctrine, the world develops on the lines of a Plan called Dialectical Materialism, first discovered by Karl Marx, embodied in the practice of a great state by Lenin, and now expounded from day to day by a Church of which Stalin is the Pope. Those who disagree with the Pope either as to doctrine or as to church government are to be liquidated if possible; if that is not possible, they are to be bamboozled. Free discussion is to be prevented wherever the power to do so exists; revelation is to be interpreted, without argument, not by democratic process, but by the dicta of ecclesiastical dignitaries. It has already become apparent that the original ethic of the early communists, like that of the early Christians, while still treated with verbal respect, is not to be followed in actual life; indeed those who would practise communism, like the Franciscans who practised apostolic poverty, are heretics, to be suppressed with the utmost rigor of persecution. If this doctrine and this organization prevail, free inquiry wiII become as impossible as it was in the middle ages, and the world wiII relapse into bigotry and obscurantism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of the Nazis, however, is definitely worse. Let us consider its salient points. There is a master race, the Germans, which is divinely ordained to rule the rest of mankind, not for their good, but for its own. Originally it was thought that races akin to the Germans
shared some of their merits, but this turned out to be a mistake; in Norway, for instance, there are no genuine Nordics except Quisling and a handful of followers. Non-Aryans are specially wicked, and the most wicked of non-Aryans are the Jews. The Japanese, on the other
band, are so virtuous that they may count as honorary Aryans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Germans, alas, have been corrupted by Jewish Influences, notably Christ and Marx. What they were before this unfortunate poison got into their blood may be seen in the pages of Tacitus. When it has been eliminated, they wiII again perceive that war is the noblest of human activities, and the opportunity of tyranny its most splendid reward. Other nations, strange to say, seem blind to the superiority of the Germans, but it was hoped that tanks and planes would prove efficient missionaries of the new creed. This hope, however, is now
rapidly fading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No such tissue of nonsense could have been believed by any population trained to examine evidence scientifically, and to base its opinions on rational grounds. Self-esteem, personal, national, or human, is one of the great sources of irrational belief; in the case of the Nazis, the self-esteem is national. Education should be directed, in part, to teaching the young to think independently of their prejudices, especially their collective prejudices, which are politically the most harmful. But this is not done anywhere; every national government finds national self-esteem useful, every rich government finds admiration of the plutocracy useful, every obscurantist government finds credulity useful. Nowhere, therefore, except among the esoteric elite of a few universities, is anything done to promote an honest attempt to decide questions according to the evidence. And so credulous populations are left defenseless against the wiles of clever politicians, who lead them through inflated self-esteem to hatred, from hatred to war, from war to universal misery. The modern advances in the art of propaganda have been met with no corresponding advances in training to resist propaganda. And so the populations of the world, one by one as &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo; reaches them, go down into a dark pit of madness, where all that is worth preserving perishes in aimless slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creed that I am preaching, if it can be called a creed, is a simple one; that, if you have an opinion about any matter, it should he based on ascertained facts, not upon hope or fear or prejudice. There is a known educational technique by which pupils of average Intelligence can be taught to discount their passions when they think, but almost everywherc the authorities prevent the use of this technique. The authorities, almost everywhere, are convinced that they
would be overthrown if the public were to examine their claims dispassionately; they therefore encourage passionate as opposed to rational thinking. Sooner or later, they become so tyrannical that they are overthrown, passionately, not rationally. After the pot of passion
has boiled long enough, a new crust forms, and the new authorities are usually no better than the old. Louis XVI is executed, and is succeeded, first by Robespierre, then by Napoleon. Tsar Nicholas is assassinated, and a strieter tyranny follows under Lenin and Stalin. To
this rule the American Revolution is one of the rare exceptions, and It was led by freethinkers; Washington and Adams, just as much as Jefferson, rejected the orthodoxy that most of their followers accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few modern obscurantists have the courage to say that it is better to believe what is false than what is true. In antiquity and In the 17th and 18th centuries It was commonly held that religion was necessary to keep the poor submissive, and should therefore be believed by them although aristocrats might have seen through it. Even in the 19th century, many French freethinkers liked their wives to be believers, In the hope that It would keep them chaste. But democracy and votes for women have made these points of view obsolete; nowadays, if you wish to advocate religion for the masses, you must advocate It for everyone, and if you are to advocate it for everyone you must do so, at least nominally, on the ground that you believe it to be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Insincerity of this appeal to truth is shown by the unwillingness to trust to free discussion or to allow the scientific habit of mind to be taught in education. If you think that a doctrine can only be rendered acceptable by the stake or the concentration camp, you evidently have not much confidence in the rational grounds In its favor. If you think it is necessary to forbid the publication or sale of books which contradict your opinions, you evidently hold that such books, in a free Intellectual competition, would be likely to get the best of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may, of course, fall back on an anti-democratic point of view. You may say: We, the Censors. or we the dignitaries of the Church, or we the agents for government propaganda, are wise men and trained Investigators; we have examined all the evidence, and reached a conclusion, which happens, by a mere coincidence, to be In line with the interest of the authorities. But the populace have not the time to study such questions deeply; subversive agitators will, if we leave them free, make appeals to vulgar passions, which it would require much time and work to combat. Since we know the truth, is it not better that we should impart it, and should forbid all attempts to cause the dissemination of what our wisdom shows to be falsehood? Let us teach humility to the public, and then tell them from time to time what we deem it good that they should know. In this way all the time spent cn futile and vexatious argumentation will be saved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the truth really is known , there is something to be said for this view. The multiplication table is taught dogmatically; a teacher who held heretical opinions about it would hardly get a job. But in such matters there is no need of censorship; no one in fact holds heretical views about the multiplication table. Heretical views arise when the truth is uncertain, and it is only when the truth is uncertain that censorship is invoked. In fact, it is difficult to find anything really certain outside the realm of pure mathematics and some facts of history and geography. If suppression of free discussion is necessary in order to cause an opinion to be believed, that in itself is evidence that the rational grounds in favor of the opinion are inadequate, for if they were adequate free discussion would be the best way of making the opinion prevail. When the authorities profess to know something which to the unprej udiced person seems doubtful or false, they are either themselves the victims of prejudice, or they are dishonestly trying to represent &amp;lsquo;the interest of their class or creed or nation as coinciding with the general interest. In either case, interference with free discussion can only do harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some one may object that, while free thought may be all very well in the abstract, it won&amp;rsquo;t do in this actual world, because fanaticism is needed for victory in battle. Other things being equal, we may be told, the holders of an irrational warlike creed will always win the
Victory over peaceful folk who only want a quiet life. There is no doubt an element of truth in this argument, but it is a small element, and what truth is contains is only for the short run. The Germans and Japanese, by means of their fanaticism, were able to win initial
Victories; but their very fanaticism roused the hostility of the world, and is leading to their downfall. Fanatics, just because they lack the scientific temper, cannot weigh risks calmly, and are prone to over-estimate the chances of Victory. In the long run, fanaticism is incompatible with scientific excellence, which is the most important source of strength in modern war. In a war between a scientific and a fanatical nation, given equal material resources, the scientific nation is pretty sure to be victorious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have wandered into political and social questions, but the core of the argument for free thought lies in the individual life. It is good to ask ourselves, from time to time, what sort of person we should wish to be. When I ask myself this question, I find that I desire at once a kind of pride and a kind of humility. As for pride: I do not wish to be forced or cajoled into any opinion because others desire that I should hold it, nor do I wish to be the victim of my own hopes and fears to the extent of allowing myself to live in an unreal world of pleasant make-believe. I respect, in myself and others, the power of thought and of scientific investigation. by means of which we have acquired whatever knowledge we possess of the universe in which we live. And thought, when it Is genuine thought, has its own intrinsic
morality and its own brand of asceticism. But it has also its rewards: a happiness, amounting at moments to ecstasy, In understanding what had been obscure, and surveying in a unified vision what had seemed detached and chaotic fragments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the pursuit of truth, when it is profound and genuine, requires also a kind of humility which has some affinity to submission to the will of God. The universe is what it is, not what I choose that it should be. If It is indifferent to human desires, as it seems to be; if human life is a passing episode, hardly noticeable in the vastness of cosmic
processes; if there is no superhuman purpose, and no hope of ultimate salvation, it is better to know and acknowledge this truth than to endeavor, in futile self-assertion, to order the universe to be what we find comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards facts, submission is the only rational attitude, but in the realm of ideals there is nothing to which to submit. The universe is neither hostile nor friendly; it neither favors our ideals nor refutes them. Our individual life is brief, and perhaps the whole life of man-
kind will be brief if measured on an astronomical scale. But that Is no reason for not Irving it as seems best to us. The things that seem to us good are none the less good for not being eternal, and we should not ask of the universe an external approval of our own ethical standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The freethinker&amp;rsquo;s universe may seem bleak and cold to those who have been accustomed to the comfortable indoor warmth of the Christian cosmology. But to those who have grown accustomed to it, it has Its own sublimity, and confers its own joys. In learning to think freely
we have learnt to thrust fear out of our thoughts, and this lesson, once learnt, brings a kind of peace which is impossible to the slave of hesitant and uncertain credulity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ON SHORTNESS OF LIFE</title>
      <link>http://habedi.github.io/post/on-shortness-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 17:45:28 +0430</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://habedi.github.io/post/on-shortness-of-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger&#34;&gt;Seneca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of mankind, Paulinus, complains about natures meanness, because our allotted span of life is so short, and because this stretch of time that is given to us runs its course so quickly, so rapidly so much so that, with very few exceptions, life leaves the rest of us in the lurch just when we re getting ready to live. And its not just the masses and the unthinking crowd that complain at what they perceive as this universal evil; the same feeling draws complaints even from men of distinction. Hence that famous dictum of the greatest of physicians: &amp;ldquo;Life is short, art long.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence also Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s grievance, most unbecoming a philosopher, when he called nature to account for bestowing so much time on animals that they can live for five or ten human life spans, while so much shorter a limit is set for humans, even though they are born to do so many great things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that we have a short time to live, but that we waste much of it. Life is long enough, and it&amp;rsquo;s been given to us in generous measure for accomplishing the greatest things, if the whole of it is well invested. But when life is squandered through soft and careless living, and when it&amp;rsquo;s spent on no worthwhile pursuit, death finally presses and we realize that the life which we didn&amp;rsquo;t notice passing has passed away. So it is: the life we are given isn&amp;rsquo;t short but we make it so; we&amp;rsquo;re not ill provided but we are wasteful of life. Just as impressive and princely wealth is squandered in an instant when it passes into the hands of a poor manager, but wealth however modest grows through careful deployment if it is entrusted to a responsible guardian, just so our lifetime offers ample scope to the person who maps it out well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we complain about nature? It has acted generously: life, if you know how to use it, is long. But one person&amp;rsquo;s held in the grip of voracious avarice, another by the kind of diligence that busies itself with pointless enterprises. This one&amp;rsquo;s sodden with wine, another slack with idleness. This one&amp;rsquo;s tired out by his political ambition, which always hangs on the judgment of others, while another&amp;rsquo;s passionate desire for trading drives him headlong over every land and every sea in hope of profit. A passion for soldiering torments some men, who are always either bent on inflicting dangers on others or worried about danger to themselves. Some are worn down by the voluntary enslavement of thankless attendance on the great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are kept busy either striving after other people&amp;rsquo;s wealth or complaining about their own. Many who have no consistent goal in life are thrown from one new design to another by a fickleness that is shifting, never settled and ever dissatisfied with itself. Some have no goal at all toward which to steer their course, but death takes them by surprise as they gape and yawn. I cannot therefore doubt the truth of that seemingly oracular utterance of the greatest of poets: &amp;ldquo;Scant is the part of life in which we live.&amp;rdquo; All the rest of existence is not living but merely time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vices assail and surround us on all sides, and they don&amp;rsquo;t allow us to rise again and lift our eyes to the clear discernment of truth; but they press down on them, keeping them lowered and fixed on mere desire. It&amp;rsquo;s never possible for their victims to return to their true selves. If by chance they ever find some respite, they still roll restlessly, just like the deep sea, which still swells even after the wind has settled; they never find full relaxation from their desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You think I&amp;rsquo;m talking only of those whose faults are admitted? Look at those whose prosperity draws crowds: they are choked by their own goods. How many have found their wealth a burden! How many are drained of their blood by their eloquence and their daily preoccupation with showing off their abilities! How many are sickly pale from their incessant pleasures! How many are left with no freedom from the multitude of their besieging clients! In short, look over all of them from lowest to highest: this person summons counsel to plead his case, another answers the call; this one stands trial, another acts for the defense, another presides as judge; no one acts as his own champion, but each is wasted for another&amp;rsquo;s sake. Ask about those influential citizens whose names are studiously memorized, and you&amp;rsquo;ll see that the following distinctions tell them apart: the first cultivates a second, the second a third; no one is his own man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again certain people give vent to the most irrational outbursts of anger: they complain about the haughtiness of their superiors, because the latter were too busy to receive them when they wanted an audience. Dare anyone complain about another&amp;rsquo;s arrogance when he himself never has time to spare for himself? Yet the great man has occasionally, albeit with a disdainful expression, condescended to look on you, whoever you are; he has deigned to listen to your words, he has allowed you to walk at his side. But you never thought fit to look on yourself or to listen to yourself. And so you&amp;rsquo;ve no reason to expect a return from anyone for those attentions of yours, since you offered them not because you wanted another&amp;rsquo;s company but because you were incapable of communing with yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though all the brilliant minds that have shone over the ages agree on this one point, they could never adequately express their astonishment at this dark fog in the human mind. No one lets anyone seize his estates, and if a trivial dispute arises about boundary lines, there&amp;rsquo;s a rush to stones and arms; but people let others trespass on their existence or rather, they go so far as to invite in those who&amp;rsquo;ll take possession of their lives. You&amp;rsquo;ll find no one willing to distribute his money; but to how many people each of us shares out his life! Men are thrifty in guarding their private property, but as soon as it comes to wasting time, they are most extravagant with the one commodity for which it&amp;rsquo;s respectable to be greedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I&amp;rsquo;d like to collar one of the older crowd: &amp;ldquo;I see that you&amp;rsquo;ve reached the limit of human life, you&amp;rsquo;re pressing hard on your hundredth year or more; come now, submit your life to an audit. Calculate how much of your time has been taken up by a moneylender, how much by a mistress, how much by a patron, how much by a client, how much in arguing with your wife, in punishing your slaves, in running about the city on social duties. Add to your calculations the illnesses that we&amp;rsquo;ve inflicted on ourselves, and also the time that has lain idle: you&amp;rsquo;ll see that you&amp;rsquo;ve fewer years than you count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look back and recall when you were ever sure of your purpose; how few days turned out as you&amp;rsquo;d intended; when you were ever at your own disposal; when your face showed its own expression; when your mind was free from disturbance; what accomplishment you can claim in such a long life; how many have plundered your existence without your being aware of what you were losing; how much time has been lost to groundless anguish, foolish pleasure, greedy desire, the charms
of society; how little is left to you from your own store of time. You&amp;rsquo;ll come to realize that you&amp;rsquo;re dying before your time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What, then, is the reason for this? Your sort live as if you&amp;rsquo;re going to live forever, your own human frailty never enters your head, you don&amp;rsquo;t keep an eye on how much time has passed already. You waste time as if it comes from a source full to overflowing, when all the while that very day which is given over to someone or something may be your last. You&amp;rsquo;re like ordinary mortals in fearing everything, you&amp;rsquo;re like immortals in coveting everything. You&amp;rsquo;ll hear many say: &amp;ldquo;After my fiftieth year I&amp;rsquo;ll retire to a life of leisure; my sixtieth year will bring release from all my duties.&amp;rdquo; And what guarantee, may I ask, do you have that your life will last longer? Who will allow those arrangements of yours to proceed according to plan? Are you not ashamed to keep for yourself only the remnants of your existence, and to allocate to philosophical thought only that portion of time which can&amp;rsquo;t be applied to any business? How late it is to begin living just when life must come to an end! What foolish obliviousness to our mortality to put off wise plans to our fiftieth and sixtieth year, and to
want to begin life from a point that few have reached!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll find that the most powerful men of high position drop words in which they pray for leisure, praise it, and prefer it to all their blessings. They sometimes long to step down from that pinnacle of theirs, if they can safely do so; for even without any external disturbance or shock, fortune crashes down on itself under its own weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The divine Augustus, to whom the gods gave more than to any man, never ceased to pray for rest for himself and to seek release from the affairs of state. Every conversation of his kept coming back to this theme, that he was hoping for leisure; he would relieve his toils with this sweet, even if illusory, consolation, the thought that one day he would live for himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a letter that he sent to the senate, when he had given an assurance that his retirement would not be wanting in dignity and not be inconsistent with his former prestige, I find the following words: &amp;ldquo;But such things are more impressive in their fulfillment than in their promise. Yet my deep desire for that time, which I have long prayed for, has led me to anticipate something of its delight by the pleasure of words, since the joy of that reality is still slow in coming.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leisure seemed such a desirable thing that, because he couldn&amp;rsquo;t enjoy it in reality, he enjoyed the thought of it in advance. He who saw that the world depended on him and him alone, who determined the fortunes of individuals and nations, he was happiest in looking forward to that day on which he would lay aside his greatness. He knew by experience how much sweat was wrung from him by those blessings that gleamed the world over; he knew the scale of the hidden anxieties they veiled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forced to contend in arms first with his fellow citizens, then with his colleagues, and finally with his relatives, he shed blood by land and sea. Driven by war through Macedonia, Sicily, Egypt, Syria, and Asia and almost every known land, he turned his armies to foreign wars when they were weary of slaughtering Romans. While he was pacifying the Alps and subjugating enemies embedded in the heart of the peaceful empire, and while he was extending its boundaries beyond the Rhine and Euphrates and Danube, in the city itself Murena, Caepio,
Lepidus, Egnatius, and others were whetting their swords against him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had not yet escaped their intrigues when his daughter and so many noble paramours, bound by adultery as if by an oath of allegiance, kept causing him alarm in his now-failing years as did Iullus and a woman once again posing a threat with her Antony. He had cut away these sores, limbs and all, but others kept growing up in their place; as if overburdened with blood, the body politic was always hemorrhaging somewhere. That is why Augustus prayed for leisure, and why he found relief from his labors in hoping for it and thinking of it; this was the prayer of the man who could grant the prayers of other men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcus Cicero was storm-tossed among the likes of Catiline and Clodius, of Pompey and Crassus, declared enemies on the one side, doubtful friends on the other. He was buffeted along with the ship of state, which he tried to keep steady as it was going down, but he was finally swept away. He was neither at ease in prosperity nor capable of withstanding adversity; how many times does he curse that very consulship of his, which he had extolled not without reason but without ceasing! How pitiful are the words that he wrings from himself in a letter written to Atticus, when the elder Pompey had been defeated and his son was still trying to revive his shattered forces in Spain! &amp;ldquo;You ask,&amp;rdquo; he says, &amp;ldquo;what I&amp;rsquo;m doing here? I&amp;rsquo;m lingering in my Tusculan estate, half-free.&amp;rdquo; After that, he goes on to other statements in which he bemoans his former life, complains about the present, and despairs of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Half-free,&amp;rdquo; Cicero said of himself. But needless to say, the sage will never resort to such an abject term. He will never be half-free but will always enjoy complete and unalloyed liberty. Not subject to any constraints, he will be his own master and tower above all others. For what can there be above the man who rises above fortune?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Livius Drusus was a vigorously energetic man who, thronged about by a huge crowd from the whole of Italy, had agitated for radical legislation and provoked the kind of troubles the Gracchi had. But he could see no clear way out for his policies, which he was unable to carry through and which, once started, it was no longer an option to abandon. He is said to have cursed the life of constant activity that he&amp;rsquo;d led from its very beginnings, saying that he was the only person who had never had a holiday even as a boy. While he was still a ward and had yet to assume the adult toga, he ventured to plead before juries on behalf of defendants and to exert his special influence in the courts to such effect, in fact, that it&amp;rsquo;s generally accepted that he captured several verdicts against the odds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where would such precocious ambition not find an outlet? You might have known that such premature presumptuousness would lead to disaster both for him and for the state. And so it was too late when he began complaining that he&amp;rsquo;d never had a holiday, since he&amp;rsquo;d been a trouble-maker and a burden to the forum from his boyhood. It is unclear whether he died by his own hand. He fell suddenly from a wound to the groin; some doubted whether his death was self-inflicted, no one that it was timely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be superfluous to mention more figures who, although they seemed to others the happiest of mortals, themselves gave true testimony against themselves when they expressed intense hatred for every act of their lives. Yet by these complaints they changed neither themselves nor anyone else; for after the outburst, their feelings reverted to their normal state. In reality, your life, even if you live a thousand years and more, will be compressed into the merest span of time; those vices of yours will swallow up any number of lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be sure, this span of time, which good management prolongs even though it naturally hurries on, must in your case escape you quickly; for you fail to seize it and hold it back, and you do nothing to delay that speediest of all things, but you allow it to pass as if it were something overabundant that we can get back again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, among the worst cases I count also those who give their time to nothing but drink and lust; for these are the most shameful preoccupations of all. Other people, even if the semblance of glory that grips them is false, nevertheless go astray in respectable fashion. You can cite for me people who are greedy, those quick to anger, or people who busy themselves with unjust hatreds or wars; but all of them sin in a more manly fashion. It is those abandoned to the belly and lust who bear the stain of dishonor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scrutinize every moment of such people&amp;rsquo;s lives, and note how much time they spend on their ledger-keeping, how much on setting traps or fearing them, how much on cultivating others or being cultivated by others, how much on giving or receiving bail, how much on dinner parties which have themselves become business: you&amp;rsquo;ll see that their affairs, whether good or bad, allow them no time to draw breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, everyone agrees that no one area of activity can be successfully pursued by someone who is preoccupied rhetoric cannot, nor can the liberal arts since the distracted mind takes
in nothing really deeply but rejects everything that is, so to speak, pounded into it. Nothing is less characteristic of a man preoccupied than living: there is no knowledge that is harder to acquire. Instructors of other disciplines are two a penny; indeed, mere boys have been seen to master some of these disciplines so thoroughly that they could even be masters in the classroom. But learning how to live takes a whole lifetime, and you&amp;rsquo;ll perhaps be more surprised at this it takes a whole lifetime to learn how to die. So many men of the highest station have set aside all their encumbrances, renounced their wealth, their business, their pleasures, and right up to the very end of life they have made it their sole aim to know how to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the majority of them depart from life admitting that they did not yet have such knowledge still less have those others attained it. Believe me, it&amp;rsquo;s the mark of a great man, and one rising above human weakness, to allow no part of his time to be skimmed off. Accordingly, such a person&amp;rsquo;s life is extremely long because he&amp;rsquo;s kept available for himself the whole of whatever amount of time he had. None of it lay fallow and uncultivated, and none of it was under another&amp;rsquo;s control; for being a most careful guardian of his time, he found nothing worth exchanging for it. And so that man had enough time; but those deprived of much of their life by the public have necessarily had too little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor should you imagine that those people aren&amp;rsquo;t sometimes conscious of their loss. Certainly you&amp;rsquo;ll hear many of those burdened by their great prosperity occasionally cry out amid their hordes of clients or their pleadings of cases or their other respectable forms of wretchedness: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve no chance to live.&amp;rdquo; Of course you don&amp;rsquo;t! All those who engage you in their business disengage you from yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many days did that defendant of yours take from you? How many that candidate? Or that old lady, wearied as she is by burying her heirs? Or that character who feigns illness to excite the greed of legacy hunters? Or that powerful friend who holds on to you not for true friendship but for show? Check off, I say, and review the days of your life: you&amp;rsquo;ll see that very few of them, and those the worthless ones, have stayed in your possession. The man who&amp;rsquo;s achieved the high office he&amp;rsquo;d prayed for longs to lay it aside and repeatedly says: &amp;ldquo;When will this year end?&amp;rdquo; The man who puts on the games thought it a great privilege that responsibility for giving them fell to him. Now he says: &amp;ldquo;When will I be free of them?&amp;rdquo; That advocate has people competing for his attention throughout the forum; with the crowd he draws, he fills the whole place further than he can be heard: &amp;ldquo;When,&amp;rdquo; he says, &amp;ldquo;will there be a vacation?&amp;rdquo; Everyone sends his life racing headlong and suffers from a longing for the future, a loathing of the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the person who devotes every second of his time to his own needs and who organizes each day as if it were a complete life neither longs for nor is afraid of the next day. For what new kind of pleasure is there that any hour can now bring? Everything has been experienced, everything enjoyed to the full. For the rest, fortune may make arrangements as it wishes; his life has already reached safety. Addition can be made to this life, but nothing taken away from it and addition made in the way that a man who is already satisfied and full takes a portion of food which he doesn&amp;rsquo;t crave and yet has room for. So there&amp;rsquo;s no reason to believe that someone has lived long because he has gray hair and wrinkles: he&amp;rsquo;s not lived long but long existed. For suppose you thought that a person had sailed far who&amp;rsquo;d been caught in a savage storm as soon as he left harbor, and after being carried in this direction and that, was driven in circles over the same course by alternations of the winds raging from different quarters: he didn&amp;rsquo;t have a long voyage, but he was long tossed about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always astonished when I see people requesting the time of others and receiving a most accommodating response from those they approach. Both sides focus on the object of the request, and neither side on time itself; it is requested as if it were nothing, granted as if it were nothing. People trifle with the most precious commodity of all; and it escapes their notice because its an immaterial thing that doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear to the eyes, and for that reason
it&amp;rsquo;s valued very cheaply or rather, it has practically no value at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People set very great store by annuities and gratuities, and forthese they hire out their services or their efforts or their attentions. But no one values time: all use it more than lavishly, as if it cost nothing. But if mortal danger threatens them, you&amp;rsquo;ll see the same people clasping their doctors&amp;rsquo; knees; if they fear a capital charge, you&amp;rsquo;ll see them ready to spend all they have to stay alive. So great is the conflict in their feelings. But if each of us could see the number of years before us as precisely as the years that have passed, how alarmed would be those who saw only a few years left, and how carefully would they use them! And yet it&amp;rsquo;s easy to manage an amount, however small, which is clearly defined; we have to be more careful in conserving an amount that may give out at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet there&amp;rsquo;s no reason to believe that those people are unaware of how precious a commodity time is. They habitually say to those they love most intensely that they are ready to give them some of their own years. And they do give them without knowing it; but they give in such a way that, without adding to the years of their loved ones, they subtract from themselves. But this very point, namely, whether they are depriving themselves, eludes them, and so they can bear the loss of what goes unnoticed in the losing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one will bring back the years, no one will restore you to your former self. Life will follow the path on which it began, and it will neither reverse nor halt its course. It will cause no commotion at all, it will call no attention to its own swiftness. It will glide on in silence. It will prolong itself at neither a king&amp;rsquo;s command nor his people&amp;rsquo;s clamor; it will run on just as it started out on the first day, with no diversions and no delays. And the outcome? You&amp;rsquo;ve been preoccupied while life hurries on; death looms all the while, and like it or not, you have to accommodate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can there be anything sillier than the view of those people who boast of their foresight? They are too busily preoccupied with efforts to live better; they plan out their lives at the expense of life itself. They form their purposes with the distant future in mind. Yet the greatest waste of life lies in postponement: it robs us of each day in turn, and snatches away the present by promising the future. The greatest impediment to living is expectancy, which relies on tomorrow and wastes today. You map out what is in fortune&amp;rsquo;s hand but let slip what&amp;rsquo;s in your own hand. What are you aiming at? What&amp;rsquo;s your goal? All that&amp;rsquo;s to come lies in uncertainty: live right now. Hear the cry of the greatest of poets, who sings his salutary song as if inspired with divine utterance: Each finest day of life for wretched mortals is ever the first to flee. &amp;ldquo;Why are you holding back?&amp;rdquo; he says. &amp;ldquo;Why are you slow to action?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t seize the day, it slips away.&amp;rdquo; Even when you&amp;rsquo;ve seized it, it will still slip away; and so you must compete with time&amp;rsquo;s quickness in the speed with which you use it, and you must drink swiftly as if from a fast-moving torrent that will not always flow. This too the poet very aptly says in chastising interminable procrastination: not each best &amp;ldquo;age&amp;rdquo; but each best &amp;ldquo;day.&amp;rdquo; Carefree and unconcerned even though time flies so quickly, why do you project for yourself months and years in long sequence, to whatever extent your greed sees fit? The poet is speaking to you about the day about this very day which is slipping away. So can there be any doubt that each finest day is ever the first to flee for wretched mortals that is, the preoccupied? Old age takes their still childish minds unawares, and they meet it unprepared and unarmed; for they&amp;rsquo;ve made no provision for it. Suddenly, unsuspecting, they&amp;rsquo;ve stumbled upon it, without noticing that it was drawing nearer every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as conversation or reading or some deep reflection beguiles travelers and they find that they&amp;rsquo;ve reached their destination before being aware of approaching it, so with this ceaseless and extremely rapid journey of life, which we make at the same pace whether awake or sleeping: the preoccupied become aware of it only at its end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I wanted to divide my subject into categories, each with its proofs, I could come up with many arguments to demonstrate that the life of the preoccupied is very short. But Fabianus, who was not one of today s chair-holding professionals but a true philosopher of the old-fashioned sort, was in the habit of saying that we must battle against the passions with a vigorous attack, not with nicety of argument; the enemy line is to be turned by a full-frontal assault, not by tiny pinpricks. He has no regard for mere quibbling, for vices are to be crushed, not merely nipped at. Nevertheless, for the preoccupied to be censured for their distinctive failing, they are to be taught a lesson, not simply given up for lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is divided into three parts: past, present, and future. Of these, the present is brief, the future doubtful, the past certain. For this last is the category over which fortune no longer has control, and which cannot be brought back under anyone&amp;rsquo;s power. Preoccupied people lose this part; for they have no leisure to look back at the past, and even if they had it, there&amp;rsquo;s no pleasure in recalling something regrettable. And so they&amp;rsquo;re unwilling to turn their minds back to times badly spent, and they dare not revisit the past because their vices become obvious in retrospect even those that insinuated themselves by the allurement of momentary pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one gladly casts his thoughts back to the past except for the person whose every action has been subjected to his own self-assessment, which is infallible. A man who&amp;rsquo;s been ambitious in the scale of his desires, arrogant in his disdainfulness, unrestrained in prevailing over others, treacherous in his deceptions, greedy in his plunderings, and lavish in his prodigality such a man must inevitably be afraid of his own memory. Yet this is the part of our existence that is consecrated and set apart, elevated above all human vicissitudes and removed beyond fortune&amp;rsquo;s sway, and harried by no poverty, no fear, no attacks of disease. This part can be neither disrupted nor stolen away; our possession of it is everlasting and untroubled. Days are present only one at a time, and these only minute by minute; but all the days of time past will attend you at your bidding, and they will allow you to examine them and hold on to them at your will something which preoccupied people have no time to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a tranquil and untroubled mind to roam freely over all the parts of life; but preoccupied minds, as if under the yoke, cannot turn around and look backward. Their life therefore disappears into an abyss; and just as it does no good to pour any amount of liquid into a vessel if there&amp;rsquo;s nothing at the bottom to receive and keep it, so it makes no difference how much time we are given if there&amp;rsquo;s nowhere for it to settle, and it&amp;rsquo;s allowed to pass through the cracks and holes in the mind. The present time is very brief indeed, so very brief that to some people it seems to be nonexistent. For it&amp;rsquo;s always in motion, slipping by and hurrying on; it ceases to be before it arrives, and it no more suffers delay than do the firmament or the heavenly bodies, whose ever-tireless movement never lets them remain in the same position. So the preoccupied are concerned with the present alone, and it is so fleeting that it can&amp;rsquo;t be grasped, and even that little amount is stolen away from them because they&amp;rsquo;re pulled in many different directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a word, do you want to know how briefly they really live? See how keen they are to live a long life. Enfeebled old men beg in their prayers for an additional few years; they pretend they are younger than they really are; they flatter themselves by this falsehood, and deceive themselves as gladly as if they deceived fate at the same time. But when some real illness has at last reminded them that they are mortal&amp;rsquo;, how terrified they are when they die, as if they&amp;rsquo;re not leaving life but are being dragged from it! They cry out repeatedly that they&amp;rsquo;ve been fools because they&amp;rsquo;ve not really lived, and that they&amp;rsquo;ll live in leisure if only they escape their illness. Then they reflect on how uselessly they made provision for things they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t live to enjoy, and how fruitless was all their toil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why should life not be ample for people who spend it far removed from all business? None of it is made over to another, none scattered in this direction or that; none of it is entrusted to fortune, none wasted through neglect; none is lost through being given away freely, none is superfluous; the whole of life yields a return, so to speak. And so, however short, it is amply sufficient; and for that reason, whenever his last day comes, the sage will not hesitate to go to his death with a sure step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You perhaps want to know whom I&amp;rsquo;d term the preoccu pied? Don&amp;rsquo;t imagine that I mean only those lawyers who are driven out of the law court only when the watchdogs are finally let in for the night; or those patrons you see crushed either with impressive display in their own crowd of admirers or more contemptuously in someone else&amp;rsquo;s crowd; or those clients whose duties summon them from their own houses in order to dash them against the doors of others; or those the praetor&amp;rsquo;s spear keeps busy for disreputable gain which is someday bound to fester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the leisure of some people is preoccupied: in their country retreat or on their couch, in the midst of their solitude, and even though they&amp;rsquo;ve withdrawn from everyone, they are troubling company for themselves; their existence is to be termed not leisurely but one of idle preoccupation. Do you call a man at leisure who arranges with meticulous attention to detail his Corinthian bronzes, which are made so expensive by the collecting mania of a few, and who spends most of the day on rusty strips of copper? Or a man who sits at a wrestling ring (for shame on us! we suffer from vices that are not even Roman), enthusiastically watching boys brawling? Who separates the troops of his own well-oiled wrestlers into pairs of the same age and skin color? Who maintains a stable of the freshest athletes? Tell me, do you call those people leisured who spend many hours at the barber&amp;rsquo;s while any overnight growth is trimmed away, solemn consultation is taken over each separate hair, and disheveled locks are rearranged or thinning hair is combed forward from both sides to cover the forehead? How angry they get if the barber has been a little too careless, as if he were cutting a real mans hair! How they flare up if anything is wrongly cut off their precious mane, if a hair lies out of place, or if everything doesn&amp;rsquo;t fall back into its proper ringlets! Which of those people wouldn&amp;rsquo;t rather have their country thrown into disarray than their hair? Who isn&amp;rsquo;t more concerned about keeping his head neat rather than safe? Who wouldn&amp;rsquo;t rather be well groomed than well respected? You call leisured these people who are kept busy between the comb and the mirror? What about those who are absorbed in composing, listening to, and learning songs? The voice, whose best and simplest flow is naturally straightforward, they twist into sinuous turns of the most feeble crooning. Their fingers are always snapping in time to some song that they carry in their head, and when they&amp;rsquo;ve been asked to attend to serious and often even sorrowful matters, you can overhear them quietly humming a tune. Theirs isn&amp;rsquo;t leisure but idle occupation. And heaven knows! I&amp;rsquo;d not class their banquets among leisurely pastimes, because I see how anxiously they arrange their silver plate, how carefully they gather up the tunics of their pretty boys-at-table, how they are on tenterhooks to see how the boar turns out from the cook, how quickly the smooth-skinned slaves hurry to discharge their duties at the given signal, how skillfully birds are carved into carefully shaped portions, and how attentively wretched little slave boys wipe away the spittle of drunks. By these means they seek a reputation for refinement and sumptuous living, and their evils follow them into every corner of their lives to such an extent that they cannot eat or drink without ostentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor would I count among the leisured those who have themselves carried around in a sedan chair and litter, and who arrive precisely on time for their rides, as if they were forbidden to skip them; and who have to be reminded of their scheduled time for bathing, for swimming, or for dining: they are so enervated by the excessive sloth of a pampered mind that they can&amp;rsquo;t tell by themselves if they are hungry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hear that one of these pampered creatures if pampered is the right word for unlearninglife and normal human practice was manually lifted out of the bath and set down in his sedan chair, and asked: &amp;ldquo;Am I now seated?&amp;rdquo; Do you think that someone like this, who doesn&amp;rsquo;t know if he is sitting, knows whether he&amp;rsquo;s alive, whether he can see, whether he&amp;rsquo;s at leisure? It&amp;rsquo;s hard for me to say whether I pity him more if he really didn&amp;rsquo;t know as much or if he pretended not to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are oblivious to many things, but they also affect forgetfulness of much. They find certain vices pleasing as evidence of their prosperity: to know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing seems to be the mark of a man who&amp;rsquo;s lowly and contemptible. What folly to think that mime actors feign many details in order to attack luxury! Truth be told, they pass over more than they fabricate, and such a wealth of unbelievable vices has arisen in an age that has applied its fertile talents in this one direction that by now we can charge the mime actors with ignoring them. To imagine that there&amp;rsquo;s anyone so ruined by pampering that he takes another&amp;rsquo;s word as to whether he&amp;rsquo;s seated! So here is not a person of leisure; you should apply a different term to him. He is sick or rather as good as dead; the truly leisured person is one who is also conscious of his own leisure. But a person who needs a guide to make him aware of his own bodily positions is only half-alive; how can he be in control of any of his time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be a long business to run through the individual cases of people who&amp;rsquo;ve spent their whole lives playing checkers or playing ball, or baking their bodies in the sun. People whose pleasures put them to considerable work are not at leisure. For instance, nobody will doubt that those who devote their time to useless literary questions Rome too now has a significant number of such people are busily engaged in doing nothing. It was once the well-known failing of the Greeks to ask how many rowers Ulysses had, whether the Iliad or the Odyssey was written first, and also whether they belong to the same author, and other questions of the same stamp which, if you keep them to yourself, do nothing to improve your private knowledge; and if you divulge them, you&amp;rsquo;re made to appear not more learned but more annoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now this vacuous enthusiasm for acquiring useless knowledge has infected the Romans as well. Only a few days ago I heard someone mentioning which Roman general had been the first to do what: Duilius was the first to win a battle at sea, Curius Dentarus the first to parade elephants in a triumph. So far, even if such items as these hardly steer us toward true glory, they still involve models of service to the state; such knowledge isn&amp;rsquo;t going to profit us, but it&amp;rsquo;s nevertheless of the sort to hold our interest because its subject matter, though empty, is appealing. We may also excuse investigators who ask who first persuaded the Romans to deploy a naval force (it was Claudius, who was called Caudex for this reason, because the ancients termed the composite structure of several planks a caudex hence the public records are called codices, and the barges which carry provisions up the Tiber are still called codicariae in accordance with ancient practice).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doubtless also this may have some relevance the fact that Valerius Corvinus was the first to conquer Messana, and was the first of the family of the Valerii to be called Messana after appropriating the name of the captured city; common usage gradually changed the lettering, so he became Messalla. But will you also allow interest in the fact that L. Sulla was the first to display lions off the leash in the circus, though as a general rule they were shown in chains, and that javelin throwers were supplied by king Bocchus to dispatch them? All right, let&amp;rsquo;s allow that as well; but is any useful purpose really served by knowing that Pompey was the first to put on a fight in the circus involving eighteen elephants, with noncriminals arrayed against them in mock battle? A leader of the state and a man of outstanding kindliness, as his reputation has it; among leaders of old, he thought it a memorable form of spectacle to destroy human beings in unheard-of fashion. &amp;ldquo;They fight to the death? That&amp;rsquo;s not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re torn to pieces? Not enough: let them be utterly crushed by animals of massive bulk!&amp;rdquo; It would certainly be preferable for such stuff to be forgotten, for fear that some future strongman might learn of it and be envious of an utterly inhuman episode. O what darkness great prosperity casts on our minds! He thought he was above the laws of nature when he was throwing so many hordes of human wretches to beasts born under a different sky, when he was arranging war between such disparate creatures, when he was shedding so much blood before the eyes of the Roman people people he&amp;rsquo;d later force to shed still more blood themselves. But this same man was later taken in by Alexandrian treachery and offered himself to be run through by the meanest of his chattels; then at last he recognized the empty boast that was his own surname.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to return to the point from which I digressed, and to demonstrate the futility of the pains that some people take in these same matters: the same source reported that Metellus, in his triumph after conquering the Carthaginians in Sicily, was alone of all Romans in having captured elephants led in procession before his chariot; and that Sulla was the last Roman to extend the pomerium, which it was the custom of old to extend after the acquisition of Italian, but never provincial, territory. Is there any more benefit in knowing this than to know that the Aventine Hill is outside the pomerium, according to him, for one of two reasons: either because that was the rallying point for the plebeians in secession from Rome, or because the birds had not been propitious when Remus took the auspices there; and to know countless other items besides that are either crammed with lies or improbable? For even if you grant that people say all these things in good faith, and even if they guarantee the truthfulness of their writing, whose mistakes will such items of information make fewer? Whose passions will they hold in check? Whom will they make braver, or more just, or more generous of spirit? My friend Fabianus used to say that he sometimes wondered whether it was better to apply oneself to no researches at all than to be embroiled in these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all people, they alone who give their time to philosophy &amp;lsquo; are at leisure, they alone really live. For it&amp;rsquo;s not just their own lifetime that they watch over carefully, but they annex every age to their own; all the years that have gone before are added to their own. Unless we prove most ungrateful, those most distinguished founders of hallowed thoughts came into being for us, and for us they prepared a way of living. We are led by the work of others into the presence of the most beautiful treasures, which have been pulled from darkness and brought to light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From no age are we debarred, we have access to all; and if we want to transcend the narrow limitations of human weakness by our expansiveness of mind, there is a great span of time for us to range over. We can debate with Socrates, entertain doubt with Carneades, be at peace with Epicurus, overcome human nature with the Stoics, and go beyond it with the Cynics. Since nature allows us shared possession of any age, why not turn from this short and fleeting passage of time and give ourselves over completely to the past, which is measureless and eternal and shared with our betters? As for those who run about performing their social duties, agitating themselves and others: when they&amp;rsquo;ve duly acted like madmen, when they&amp;rsquo;ve crossed every threshold on their daily rounds and passed no open door, and when they&amp;rsquo;ve delivered their moneygrubbing greeting to houses very distant from one another, how few patrons will they be able to catch sight of in a city so vast and so fragmented by varied passions! How many patrons will there be whose sleep or self-indulgence or churlishness denies their callers access! How many who, after they&amp;rsquo;ve tortured them with the long wait, pretend to be in a hurry as they pass them by! How many will avoid going out through a reception hall packed with clients and make their escape through a door that&amp;rsquo;s hidden from view, as if it were not even cruder to deceive them than to refuse them admittance! How many, half- asleep and weighed down by the effects of yesterday&amp;rsquo;s drinking, will yawn with utter disdain and address those wretched clients, who cut short their own sleep in order to wait on another&amp;rsquo;s, by the right name only after it&amp;rsquo;s been whispered to them a thousand times over by lips that hardly move! Do we suppose these clients spend time on morally commendable duties? But we can say as much of those who&amp;rsquo;ll want to have Zeno, Pythagoras, Democritus, and the other high priests of philosophical study, and Aristotle and Theophrastus, as their closest companions every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these will ever be unavailable to you, none of these will fail to send his visitor off in a happier condition and more at ease with himself. None will let anyone leave empty handed; they can be approached by all mortals by night and by day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these philosophers will force you to die, but all will teach you how. None of them will diminish your years, but each will share his own years with you. With none of them will conversation be dangerous, friendship life threatening, or cultivation of them expensive. From them you&amp;rsquo;ll take whatever you wish; it will be no fault of theirs if you fail to take in the very fullest amount you have room for. What happiness, what a fine old age lies in store for the person who&amp;rsquo;s put himself under the patronage of these people! He&amp;rsquo;ll have friends whose advice he can seek on the greatest or least important matters, whom he can consult daily about himself, from whom he can hear the truth without insult and receive praise without fawning,
and who will provide a model after which to fashion himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common saying that it was not in our power to choose the parents we were allotted, and that they were given to us by chance; yet we can be born to whomever we wish. There are households of the most distinguished intellects: choose the one into which you&amp;rsquo;d like to be adopted, and you&amp;rsquo;ll inherit not just the name but also the actual property, which is not to be hoarded in a miserly or mean spirit: the more people you share it with, the greater it will become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These will open for you the path to immortality, and raise you to an elevation from which no one is cast down. This is the sole means of prolonging mortality, or rather of transforming it into immortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honors, monuments, all that ostentatious ambition has ordered by decree or erected in stone, are soon destroyed: there&amp;rsquo;s nothing that the long lapse of time doesn&amp;rsquo;t demolish and transform. But it cannot harm the works consecrated by wisdom: no age will efface them, no age reduce them at all. The next age and each one after that will only enhance the respect in which they are held, since envy focuses on what is close at hand, but we more freely admire things from a distance. So the sage&amp;rsquo;s life is ample in scope, and he&amp;rsquo;s not constricted by the same limit that confines others. He alone is released from the limitations of the human race, and he is master of all ages as though a god. Some time has passed? He holds it in recollection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is upon us? He uses it. Time is to come? This he anticipates. The combining of all times into one makes his life long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for those who forget the past, disregard the present, and fear for the future, life is very brief and very troubled. When they reach the end of it, they realize too late, poor wretches, that they&amp;rsquo;ve been busied for so long in doing nothing. And the fact that they sometimes pray for death need hardly be taken as evidence that their life is long. In their folly they are afflicted by fickle feelings that rush them into the very things they fear; they often pray for death precisely because they fear it. And there&amp;rsquo;s no reason to find evidence that they live long in the fact that the day often seems long to them, or that they complain that the hours pass slowly until the appointed hour for dinner arrives; for when their usual preoccupations fail them and they are left with nothing to do, they fret without knowing how to apply their free time or how to drag it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so they move on to some other preoccupation and find all the intervening time burdensome, precisely as they do when a gladiatorial show has been announced for a given day, or when the date of some other show or amusement is keenly awaited, and they want to skip over the days in between. Any postponement of something they look forward to is long to them. But the time of actual enjoyment is short and fleeting, and made far shorter by their own fault; for they desert one pleasure for another and cannot persist steadily in any one desire. Their days aren&amp;rsquo;t long but hateful; yet, on the other hand, how short seem the nights that they spend cavorting with prostitutes or drinking! Hence the mad inspiration of poets too who feed human frailty by their stories and imagine that Jupiter actually doubled the length of the night when seduced by sexual pleasure. All this inflaming of our worst passions amounts to nothing but enlisting the gods as setting a precedent for our vices, and giving a license for corruption that is justified by divine example. How can the nights that they pay for so dearly not seem so very short to these people? They lose the day in looking forward to the night, the night in fear of the dawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very pleasures of such people are anxious and disturbed by various kinds of alarm, and at the very moment when they are rejoicing the agitated thought steals in on them: &amp;ldquo;How long will this last?&amp;rdquo; It is this feeling that has caused kings to weep over their own power; the extent of their prosperity gave them no pleasure, but the prospect of its eventual end terrified them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When that exceedingly arrogant king of the Persians ranged his army over the vast plains and could only measure its size, not count it, he wept at the thought that within a century not one soldier from that huge force would still be alive. Yet the very man who wept was destined to bring their fate on them, to lose some troops at sea, others on land, some in battle, others in flight, and so to destroy in a very short time all those for whose hundredth year he feared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what of the fact that even the joys of such people are anxiety ridden? This is because they don&amp;rsquo;t rest on stable causes but are disrupted as frivolously as they are produced. But what do you think their times are like when they are wretched even by their own admission, since even the joys which lift and transport them above their fellow men are by no means unmixed? All the greatest blessings cause anxiety, and fortune is never less wisely trusted than when at its most advantageous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maintain prosperity we need fresh prosperity, and other prayers are to be offered instead of those that have already turned out well. Everything that comes our way by chance is unsteady, and the hi&amp;rsquo;gher our fortunes rise, the more susceptible they are to falling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what must inevitably collapse gives no one pleasure; and so the life of those who acquire through hard work what they must work harder to possess is necessarily very wretched, and not just very brief. They obtain with great effort what they desire, and they anxiously hold on to what they&amp;rsquo;ve obtained; and meanwhile they give no consideration to time&amp;rsquo;s irretrievability. New preoccupations take the place of old, hope arouses new hope, ambition new ambition. They don&amp;rsquo;t look for an end to their wretchedness, but change the cause of it. We&amp;rsquo;ve been tormented by our own public office? We spend more time on somebody else&amp;rsquo;s. We&amp;rsquo;ve stopped toiling as candidates? We start canvassing for others. We&amp;rsquo;ve given up the vexation of being a prosecutor? We take on that of being a judge. A man stops being a judge? He starts presiding over a special commission. A man&amp;rsquo;s spent all his working life managing other people&amp;rsquo;s property for a salary?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He&amp;rsquo;s diverted by looking after his own wealth. Marius was done with army service, and the consulship kept him busy. Quintius hurries to get through his dictatorship, but he&amp;rsquo;ll be called back to it from his plow. Scipio will go up against the Carthaginians before being
fully ready for such an undertaking. Victorious over Hannibal, victorious over Antiochus, he will win distinction in his own consulship and act as surety for his brother&amp;rsquo;s consulship; and but for his own objections, his statue would be placed in Jupiter&amp;rsquo;s company in the Capitoline temple. But discord among the citizens will bring trouble to their savior, and after he has scorned as a young man public honors rivaling those of the gods, in old age he&amp;rsquo;ll eventually take pleasure in an ostentatiously defiant exile. Reasons for anxiety will never be wanting, whether because of prosperity or wretchedness. Life will be driven on through one preoccupation after another; we shall always pray for leisure but never attain it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, my dearest Paulinus, remove yourself from the crowd and, storm-tossed more than your years deserve, withdraw at last to a more peaceful haven. Consider how many waves you&amp;rsquo;ve endured and, on the one side, how many storms you&amp;rsquo;ve weathered in private and, on the other, how many you&amp;rsquo;ve brought on yourself in your public career. Long enough has your virtue been demonstrated through toilsome and unceasing proofs; put to the test what it can achieve in leisure. The greater part of your life, and certainly the better part, has been given to the state: take some of your time for yourself as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not to a sluggish and idle state of inaction that I summon you, or to drown all your lively energy in sleep and in the pleasures that are dear to the crowd. That&amp;rsquo;s not to find peace of mind: you&amp;rsquo;ll find tasks to busy yourself about in serene seclusion that are more important than any you&amp;rsquo;ve dealt with so energetically thus far. You manage the revenues of the world, it is true, as scru- pulously as you would a stranger&amp;rsquo;s, as diligently as you would your own, as conscientiously as you would the state&amp;rsquo;s. You win affection in a post in which it is hard to avoid being hated. Yet it is nevertheless better believe me to know the balance sheet of one&amp;rsquo;s own life than that of the public grain supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall that energetic mind of yours, which is supremely qualified to deal with the greatest challenges, from an office that is certainly eminent but is hardly in keeping with the happy life. And consider that you didn&amp;rsquo;t make it your aim, with all your training in the liberal arts from the earliest age, for many thousands of grain measures to be safely entrusted to you; you&amp;rsquo;d shown promise of something greater and higher. There&amp;rsquo;ll be no shortage of men of both scrupulous good character and diligent service. But slow-moving pack animals are far better suited to carrying heavy loads than thoroughbred horses; who ever hampered the fleetness of these well-bred creatures with a weighty burden? Consider, moreover, how stressful it is to subject yourself to such a heavy responsibility; you have to deal with the human stomach, and a hungry people neither submits to reason nor is soothed by fair treatment or influenced by any entreaty. Only recently, within those few days after Gaius Caesar died, he was still pained to the utmost (if the dead have any consciousness) because he saw that the Roman people survived him and still had enough rations for seven or at all events eight days; because he made his bridges of boats and played with the empire&amp;rsquo;s resources, we faced the worst kind of disaster even for people under siege: a shortage of food. His imitation of a crazed foreign king of ill-fated arrogance almost came at the cost of mass destruction by starvation, and of the general catastrophe that follows famine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was the frame of mind of the officials in charge of the grain supply when they were destined to face stones, weapons, fires, and Gaius? With the greatest concealment they covered over such a great sickness lurking amid the state&amp;rsquo;s innermost organs, and with good reason, to be sure. For certain complaints are to be treated without the patient&amp;rsquo;s being aware of them; knowing about their disease has caused many to die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retire to those pursuits that are calmer, safer, and more important. Do you think it amounts to the same thing whether you&amp;rsquo;re in charge of seeing that imported grain is transferred to the granaries undamaged by either the dishonesty or the carelessness of the transporters, that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t absorb moisture and then get spoiled through heat, and that it corresponds to the declared weight and measure; or whether you occupy yourself with these hallowed and lofty studies, so as to learn the substance of god, his will, his general character, and his shape; what outcome awaits your soul; where nature lays us to rest upon release from our bodies; what it is that bears the weight of all the heaviest matter of this world in the center, suspends the light components above, carries fire to the highest part, and rouses the stars to their given changes of movement; and to learn other such matters in turn that are full of great wonders? You really ought to leave ground level and turn your mind&amp;rsquo;s eye to these studies. Now, while enthusiasm is still fresh, those with an active interest should progress to better things. In this mode of life much that is worth studying awaits you: the love and practice of the virtues, forgetfulness of the passions, knowledge of how to live and to die, and deep
repose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plight of all preoccupied people is wretched, but most wretched is the plight of those who labor under preoccupations that are not even their own, whose sleep schedule is regulated by somebody else&amp;rsquo;s, who walk at somebody else&amp;rsquo;s pace, and who are under instructions in that freest of all activities loving and hating. If these people want to know how short their life is, let them reflect on how small a part of it is their very own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when you see a man repeatedly taking up the robe of office, or a name well known in public, don&amp;rsquo;t envy him: those trappings are bought at the cost of life. For one year to be dated by their name, they&amp;rsquo;ll waste all their own years. Life deserts some of them amid their first struggles, before the arduous climb up to the peak of their ambition. Some, after they&amp;rsquo;ve clambered up through a thousand indignities to arrive at the crowning dignity, are assailed by the wretched thought that all their toil has been for an inscription on an epitaph. Some map out new aspirations for their extreme old age as if in their youth, and they succumb to weakness amid their great and immoderate endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a shameful end when an old man acting in court for litigants who are perfectly unknown to him breathes his last even at the moment when he&amp;rsquo;s winning the applause of impressionable bystanders. It&amp;rsquo;s a disgraceful end when the man who&amp;rsquo;s sooner worn out by living than by working drops dead in the middle of his duties; and a disgraceful end when a man dies in the act of going over his accounts and draws a smile from the heir who&amp;rsquo;s long been kept waiting. I can&amp;rsquo;t pass over one example that occurs to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaius Turannius was an old man of proven diligence who was past ninety when, on the emperor&amp;rsquo;s initiative, he was granted retirement from his administrative post by Gaius Caesar; he gave instructions for himself to be laid out on his bed and to be mourned by his assembled household as if he were dead. The house lamented its elderly master&amp;rsquo;s unemployment and didn&amp;rsquo;t cease their mourning until his job was restored to him. Is it really such a pleasure to die preoccupied?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet many have that same attitude, and their desire for work lasts longer than their capacity for it. They struggle against their bodily infirmity, and old age itself they adjudge a hardship for no other reason than because it removes them from office. The law doesn&amp;rsquo;t draft a soldier after fifty, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t require a senator&amp;rsquo;s attendance after sixty: it&amp;rsquo;s harder for people to obtain retirement from themselves than from the law. All the time while they plunder and are plundered and break in on each other&amp;rsquo;s rest and make each other miserable, life is without profit, without pleasure, without any progress of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one holds death in view, no one refrains from distant hopes. Indeed, some people even make arrangements for things beyond life huge tomb structures, dedications of public buildings, gladiatorial shows for the funeral, and ostentatious funeral processions. Yet in truth, the funerals of such people should be conducted by the light of torches and wax tapers, as if they&amp;rsquo;d lived for the briefest span.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Translated By: Garreth Williams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THE AMERICAN SCHOLAR</title>
      <link>http://habedi.github.io/post/american-scholar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 19:20:14 +0430</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://habedi.github.io/post/american-scholar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph_Waldo_Emerson&#34;&gt;Ralph Waldo Emerson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This address was delivered at Cambridge in 1837, before the Harvard Chapter of the Phi Beta Kappa Society, a college fraternity composed of the first twenty-five men in each    graduating class. The society has annual meetings, which have been the occasion for addresses from the most distinguished scholars and thinkers of the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. President and Gentlemen,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I greet you on the recommencement of our literary year. Our anniversary is one of hope, and, perhaps, not enough of labor. We do not meet for games of strength or skill, for the recitation of histories, tragedies, and odes, like the ancient Greeks; for parliaments of love and poesy, like the Troubadours; nor for the advancement of science, like our co-temporaries in the British and European capitals. Thus far, our holiday has been simply a friendly sign of the survival of the love of letters amongst a people too busy to give to letters any more. As such it is precious as the sign of an indestructible instinct. Perhaps the time is already come when it ought to be, and will be, something else; when the sluggard intellect of this continent will look from under its iron lids and fill the postponed expectation of the world with something better than the exertions of mechanical skill. Our day of dependence, our long apprenticeship to the learning of other lands, draws to a close. The millions that around us are rushing into life cannot always be fed on the sere remains of foreign harvests. Events, actions arise that must be sung, that will sing themselves. Who can doubt that poetry will revive and lead in a new age, as the star in the constellation Harp, which now flames in our zenith, astronomers announce, shall one day be the pole-star for a thousand years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the light of this hope I accept the topic which not only usage but the nature of our association seem to prescribe to this day, the American Scholar. Year by year we come up hither to read one more chapter of his biography. Let us inquire what new lights, new events, and more days have thrown on his character, his duties, and his hopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is one of those fables which out of an unknown antiquity convey an unlooked-for wisdom, that the gods, in the beginning, divided Man into men, that he might be more helpful to himself; just as the hand was divided into fingers, the better to answer its end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old fable covers a doctrine ever new and sublime; that there is One Man, present to all particular men only partially, or through one faculty; and that you must take the whole society to find the whole man. Man is not a farmer, or a professor, or an engineer, but he is all. Man is priest, and scholar, and statesman, and producer, and soldier. In the divided or social state these functions are parceled out to individuals, each of whom aims to do his stint of the joint work, whilst each other performs his. The fable implies that the individual, to possess himself, must sometimes return from his own labor to embrace all the other laborers. But, unfortunately, this original unit, this fountain of power, has been so distributed to multitudes, has been so minutely subdivided and peddled out, that it is spilled into drops, and cannot be gathered. The state of society is one in which the members have suffered amputation from the trunk and strut about so many walking monsters a good finger, a neck, a stomach, an elbow, but never a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man is thus metamorphosed into a thing, into many things. The planter, who is Man sent out into the field to gather food, is seldom cheered by any idea of the true dignity of his ministry. He sees his bushel and his cart, and nothing beyond, and sinks into the farmer, instead of Man on the farm. The tradesman scarcely ever gives an ideal worth to his work, but is ridden by the routine of his craft, and the soul is subject to dollars. The priest becomes a form; the attorney a statute-book; the mechanic a machine; the sailor a rope of the ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this distribution of functions the scholar is the delegated intellect. In the right state he is Man Thinking. In the degenerate state, when the victim of society, he tends to become a mere thinker, or, still worse, the parrot of other men&amp;rsquo;s thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this view of him, as Man Thinking, the whole theory of his office is contained. Him Nature solicits with all her placid, all her monitory pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Him the past instructs. Him the future invites. Is not indeed every man a student, and do not all things exist for the student&amp;rsquo;s behoof? And, finally, is not the true scholar the only true master? But as the old oracle said, &amp;ldquo;All things have two handles: Beware of the wrong one.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In life, too often, the scholar errs with mankind and forfeits his privilege. Let us see him in his school, and consider him in reference to the main influences he receives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I. The first in time and the first in importance of the influences upon the mind is that of nature. Every day, the sun; and, after sunset, Night and her stars. Ever the winds blow; ever the grass grows. Every day, men and women, conversing, beholding and beholden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scholar must needs stand wistful and admiring before this great spectacle. He must settle its value in his mind. What is nature to him? There is never a beginning, there is never an end, to the inexplicable continuity of this web of God, but always circular power returning into itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therein it resembles his own spirit, whose beginning, whose ending, he never can find so entire, so boundless. Far too as her splendors shine, system on system shooting like rays, upward, downward, without center, without circumference in the mass and in the particle, Nature hastens to render account of herself to the mind. Classification begins. To the young mind everything is individual, stands by itself. By and by it finds how to join two things and see in them one nature; then three, then three thousand; and so, tyrannized over by its own unifying instinct, it goes on tying things together, diminishing anomalies, discovering roots running under ground whereby contrary and remote things cohere and flower out from one stem. It presently learns that since the dawn of history there has been a constant accumulation and classifying of facts. But what is classification but the perceiving that these objects are not chaotic, and are not foreign, but have a law which is also a law of the human mind? The astronomer discovers that geometry, a pure abstraction of the human mind, is the measure of planetary motion. The chemist finds proportions and intelligible method throughout matter; and science is nothing but the finding of analogy, identity, in the most remote parts. The ambitious soul sits down before each refractory fact; one after another reduces all strange constitutions, all new powers, to their class and their law, and goes on forever to animate the last fiber of organization, the outskirts of nature, by insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus to him, to this school-boy under the bending dome of day, is suggested that he and it proceed from one Root; one is leaf and one is flower; relation, sympathy, stirring in every vein. And what is that root? Is not that the soul of his soul?A thought too bold?A dream too wild? Yet when this spiritual light shall have revealed the law of more earthly natures when he has learned to worship the soul, and to see that the natural philosophy that now is, is only the first gropings of its gigantic hand he shall look forward to an ever-expanding knowledge as to a becoming creator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He shall see that nature is the opposite of the soul, answering to it part for part. One is seal and one is print. Its beauty is the beauty of his own mind. Its laws are the laws of his own mind. Nature then becomes to him the measure of his attainments. So much of nature as he is ignorant of, so much of his own mind does he not yet possess. And, in fine, the ancient precept, &amp;ldquo;Know thyself,&amp;rdquo; and the modern precept, &amp;ldquo;Study nature,&amp;rdquo; become at last one maxim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;II. The next great influence into the spirit of the scholar is the mind of the Past in whatever form, whether of literature, of art, of institutions, that mind is inscribed. Books are the best type of the influence of the past, and perhaps we shall get at the truth learn the amount of this influence more conveniently by considering their value alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of books is noble. The scholar of the first age received into him the world around; brooded thereon; gave it the new arrangement of his own mind, and uttered it again. It came into him life; it went out from him truth. It came to him short-lived actions; it went out from him immortal thoughts. It came to him business; it went from him poetry. It was dead fact; now, it is quick thought. It can stand, and it can go. It now endures, it now flies, it now inspires. Precisely in proportion to the depth of mind from which it issued, so high does it soar, so long does it sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, I might say, it depends on how far the process had gone, of transmuting life into truth. In proportion to the completeness of the distillation, so will the purity and imperishableness of the product be. But none is quite perfect. As no air-pump can by any means make a perfect vacuum, so neither can any artist entirely exclude the conventional, the local, the perishable from his book, or write a book of pure thought, that shall be as efficient, in all respects, to a remote posterity, as to contemporaries, or rather to the second age. Each age, it is found, must write its own books; or rather, each generation for the next succeeding. The books of an older period will not fit this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet hence arises a grave mischief. The sacredness which attaches to the act of creation, the act of thought, is instantly transferred to the record. The poet chanting was felt to be a divine man. Henceforth the chant is divine also. The writer was a just and wise spirit. Henceforward it is settled the book is perfect; as love of the hero corrupts into worship of his statue. Instantly the book becomes noxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide is a tyrant. We sought a brother, and lo, a governor. The sluggish and perverted mind of the multitude, always slow to open to the incursions of Reason, having once so opened, having once received this book, stands upon it, and makes an outcry if it is disparaged. Colleges are built on it. Books are written on it by thinkers, not by Man Thinking, by men of talent, that is, who start wrong, who set out from accepted dogmas, not from their own sight of principles. Meek young men grow up in libraries, believing it their duty to accept the views which Cicero, which Locke, which Bacon, have given; forgetful that Cicero, Locke and Bacon were only young men in libraries when they wrote these books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, instead of Man Thinking, we have the bookworm. Hence the book-learned class, who value books, as such; not as related to nature and the human constitution, but as making a sort of Third Estate with the world and soul. Hence the restorers of readings, the emendators, the bibliomaniacs of all degrees. This is bad; this is worse than it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books are the best of things, well used; abused, among the worst. What is the right use? What is the one end which all means go to effect? They are for nothing but to inspire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had better never see a book than to be warped by its attraction clean out of my own orbit, and made a satellite instead of a system. The one thing in the world of value is the active soul the soul, free, sovereign, active. This every man is entitled to; this every man contains within him, although in almost all men obstructed, and as yet unborn. The soul active sees absolute truth and utters truth, or creates. In this action it is genius; not the privilege of here and there a favorite, but the sound estate of every man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its essence it is progressive. The book, the college, the school of art, the institution of any kind, stop with some past utterance of genius. This is good, say they let us hold by this. They pin me down.
They look backward and not forward. But genius always looks forward. The eyes of man are set in his forehead, not in his hindhead. Man hopes. Genius creates. To create to create is the proof of a divine presence. Whatever talents may be, if the man create not, the pure efflux of the Deity is not his; cinders and smoke there may be, but not yet flame. There are creative manners, there are creative actions, and creative words; manners, actions, words, that is, indicative of no custom or authority, but springing spontaneous from the mind&amp;rsquo;s own sense of good and fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other part, instead of being its own seer, let it receive always from another mind its truth, though it were in torrents of light, without periods of solitude, inquest, and self-recovery; and a fatal disservice is done. Genius is always sufficiently the enemy of genius by over-influence.
The literature of every nation bear me witness. The English dramatic poets have Shakespearized now for two hundred years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly there is a right way of reading, so it be sternly subordinated. Man Thinking must not be subdued by his instruments. Books are for the scholar&amp;rsquo;s idle times. When he can read God directly, the hour is too precious to be wasted in other men&amp;rsquo;s transcripts of their readings. But when the intervals of darkness come, as come they must when the soul seeth not, when the sun is hid and the stars withdraw their shining we repair to the lamps which were kindled by their ray, to guide our steps to the East again, where the dawn is. We hear, that we may speak. The Arabian proverb says, &amp;ldquo;A fig-tree, looking on a fig-tree, becometh fruitful.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is remarkable, the character of the pleasure we derive from the best books. They impress us ever with the conviction that one nature wrote and the same reads. We read the verses of one of the great English poets, of Chaucer, of Marvell, of Dryden, with the most modern joy, with a pleasure, I mean, which is in great part caused by the abstraction of all time from their verses. There is some awe mixed with the joy of our surprise, when this poet, who lived in some past world, two or three hundred years ago, says that which lies close to my own soul, that which I also had well-nigh thought and said. But for the evidence thence afforded to the philosophical doctrine of the identity of all minds, we should suppose some pre-established harmony, some foresight of souls that were to be, and some preparation of stores for their future wants, like the fact observed in insects, who lay up food before death for the young grub they shall never see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not be hurried by any love of system, by any exaggeration of instincts, to underrate the Book. We all know that as the human body can be nourished on any food, though it were boiled grass and the broth of shoes, so the human mind can be fed by any knowledge. And great and heroic men have existed who had almost no other information than by the printed page. I only would say that it needs a strong head to bear that diet. One must be an inventor to read well. As the proverb says, &amp;ldquo;He that would bring home the wealth of the Indies must carry out the wealth of the Indies.&amp;rdquo; There is then creative reading as well as creative writing. When the mind is braced by labor and invention, the page of whatever book we read becomes luminous with manifold allusion. Every sentence is doubly significant, and the sense of our author is as broad as the world. We then see, what is always true, that as the seer&amp;rsquo;s hour of vision is short and rare among heavy days and months, so is its record, perchance, the least part of his volume. The discerning will read, in his Plato or Shakespeare, only that least part only the authentic utterances of the oracle; all the rest he rejects, were it never so many times Plato&amp;rsquo;s and Shakespeare&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there is a portion of reading quite indispensable to a wise man. History and exact science he must learn by laborious reading. Colleges, in like manner, have their indispensable office, to teach elements. But they can only highly serve us when they aim not to drill, but to create; when they gather from far every ray of various genius to their hospitable halls, and by the concentrated fires set the hearts of their youth on flame. Thought and knowledge are natures in which apparatus and pretension avail nothing. Gowns and pecuniary foundations, though of towns of gold, can never countervail the least sentence or syllable of wit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forget this, and our American colleges will recede in their public importance, whilst they grow richer every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;III. There goes in the world a notion that the scholar should be a recluse, a valetudinarian, as unfit for any handiwork or public labor as a penknife for an axe. The so-called &amp;ldquo;practical men&amp;rdquo; sneer at speculative men, as if, because they speculate or see, they could do nothing. I have heard it said that the clergy who are always, more universally than any other class, the scholars of their dayare addressed as women; that the rough, spontaneous conversation of men they do not hear, but only a mincing and diluted speech. They are often virtually disfranchised; and indeed there are advocates for their celibacy. As far as this is true of the studious classes, it is not just and wise. Action is with the scholar subordinate, but it is essential. Without it he is not yet man. Without it thought can never ripen into truth. Whilst the world hangs before the eye as a cloud of beauty, we cannot even see its beauty. Inaction is cowardice, but there can be no scholar without the heroic mind. The preamble of thought, the transition through which it passes from the unconscious to the conscious, is action. Only so much do I know, as I have lived. Instantly we know whose words are loaded with life, and whose not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world this shadow of the soul, or other me, lies wide around. Its attractions are the keys which unlock my thoughts and make me acquainted with myself. I launch eagerly into this resounding tumult. I grasp the hands of those next me, and take my place in the ring to suffer and to work, taught by an instinct that so shall the dumb abyss be vocal with speech. I pierce its order; I dissipate its fear; I dispose of it within the circuit of my expanding life. So much only of life as I know by experience, so much of the wilderness have I vanquished and planted, or so far have I extended my being, my dominion. I do not see how any man can afford, for the sake of his nerves and his nap, to spare any action in which he can partake. It is pearls and rubies to his discourse. Drudgery, calamity, exasperation, want, are instructors in eloquence and wisdom. The true scholar grudges every opportunity of action passed by, as a loss of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the raw material out of which the intellect molds her splendid products. A strange process too, this by which experience is converted into thought, as a mulberry-leaf is converted into satin. The manufacture goes forward at all hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actions and events of our childhood and youth are now matters of calmest observation. They lie like fair pictures in the air. Not so with our recent actions with the business which we now have in hand. On this we are quite unable to speculate. Our affections as yet circulate through it. We no more feel or know it than we feel the feet, or the hand, or the brain of our body. The new deed is yet a part of life remains for a time immersed in our unconscious life. In some contemplative hour it detaches itself from the life like a ripe fruit, to become a thought of the mind. Instantly it is raised, transfigured; the corruptible has put on incorruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henceforth it is an object of beauty, however base its origin and neighborhood. Observe, too, the impossibility of antedating this act. In its grub state it cannot fly, it cannot shine, it is a dull grub. But suddenly, without observation, the selfsame thing unfurls beautiful wings, and is an angel of wisdom. So is there no fact, no event, in our private history, which shall not, sooner or later, lose its adhesive, inert form, and astonish us by soaring from our body into the empyrean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cradle and infancy, school and playground, the fear of boys, and dogs, and ferules, the love of little maids and berries, and many another fact that once filled the whole sky, are gone already; friend and relative, profession and party, town and country, nation and world, must also soar and sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, he who has put forth his total strength in fit actions has the richest return of wisdom. I will not shut myself out of this globe of action, and transplant an oak into a flower-pot, there to hunger and pine; nor trust the revenue of some single faculty, and exhaust one vein of thought, much like those Savoyards, who, getting their livelihood by carving shepherds, shepherdesses, and smoking Dutchmen, for all Europe, went out one day to the mountain to find stock, and discovered that they had whittled up the last of their pine-trees. Authors we have, in numbers, who have written out their vein, and who, moved by a commendable prudence, sail for Greece or Palestine, follow the trapper into the prairie, or ramble round Algiers, to replenish their merchantable stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it were only for a vocabulary, the scholar would be covetous of action. Life is our dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years are well spent in country labors; in town; in the insight into trades and manufactures; in frank intercourse with many men and women; in science; in art; to the one end of mastering in all their facts a language by which to illustrate and embody our perceptions. I learn immediately from any speaker how much he has already lived, through the poverty or the splendor of his speech. Life lies behind us as the quarry from whence we get tiles and copestones for the masonry of today. This is the way to learn grammar. Colleges and books only copy the language which the field and the work-yard made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the final value of action, like that of books, and better than books, is that it is a resource. That great principle of Undulation in nature, that shows itself in the inspiring and expiring of the breath; in desire and satiety; in the ebb and flow of the sea; in day and night; in heat and cold; and, as yet more deeply ingrained in every atom and every fluid, is known to us under the name of Polarity these &amp;ldquo;fits of easy transmission and reflection,&amp;rdquo; as Newton called them, are the law of nature because they are the law of spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mind now thinks, now acts, and each fit reproduces the other. When the artist has exhausted his materials, when the fancy no longer paints, when thoughts are no longer apprehended and books are a weariness he has always the resource to live. Character is higher than intellect. Thinking is the function. Living is the functionary. The stream retreats to its source. A great soul will be strong to live, as well as strong to think. Does he lack organ or medium to impart his truth? He can still fall back on this elemental force of living them. This is a total act. Thinking is a partial act. Let the grandeur of justice shine in his affairs. Let the beauty of affection cheer his lowly roof. Those &amp;ldquo;far from fame,&amp;rdquo; who dwell and act with him, will feel the force of his constitution in the doings and passages of the day better than it can be measured by any public and designed display. Time shall teach him that the scholar loses no hour which the man lives. Herein he unfolds the sacred germ of his instinct, screened from influence. What is lost in seemliness is gained in strength. Not out of those on whom systems of education have exhausted their culture comes the helpful giant to destroy the old or to build the new, but out of unhandselled savage nature; out of terrible Druids and Berserkers come at last Alfred and Shakespeare. I hear therefore with joy whatever is beginning to be said of the dignity and necessity of labor to every citizen. There is virtue yet in the hoe and the spade, for learned as well as for unlearned hands. And labor is everywhere welcome; always we are invited to work; only be this limitation observed, that a man shall not for the sake of wider activity sacrifice any opinion to the popular judgments and modes of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now spoken of the education of the scholar by nature, by books, and by action. It remains to say somewhat of his duties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are such as become Man Thinking. They may all be comprised in self-trust. The office of the scholar is to cheer, to raise, and to guide men by showing them facts amidst appearances. He plies the slow, unhonored, and unpaid task of observation. Flamsteed and Herschel, in their glazed observatories, may catalogue the stars with the praise of all men, and, the results being splendid and useful, honor is sure. But he, in his private observatory, cataloguing obscure and nebulous stars of the human mind, which as yet no man has thought of as such, watching days and months sometimes for a few facts; correcting still his old records, must relinquish display and immediate fame. In the long period of his preparation he must betray often an ignorance and shiftlessness in popular arts, incurring the disdain of the able who shoulder him aside. Long he must stammer in his speech; often forego the living for the dead. Worse yet, he must accept how often! poverty and solitude. For the ease and pleasure of treading the old road, accepting the fashions, the education, the religion of society, he takes the cross of making his own, and, of course, the self-accusation, the faint heart, the frequent uncertainty and loss of time, which are the nettles and tangling vines in the way of the self-relying and self-directed; and the state of virtual hostility in which he seems to stand to society, and especially to educated society. For all this loss and scorn, what offset? He is to find consolation in exercising the highest functions of human nature. He is one who raises himself from private considerations and breathes and lives on public and illustrious thoughts. He is the world&amp;rsquo;s eye. He is the world&amp;rsquo;s heart. He is to resist the vulgar prosperity that retrogrades ever to barbarism, by preserving and communicating heroic sentiments, noble biographies, melodious verse, and the conclusions of history. Whatsoever oracles the human heart, in all emergencies, in all solemn hours, has uttered as its commentary on the world of actions these he shall receive and impart. And whatsoever new verdict Reason from her inviolable seat pronounces on the passing men and events of today, this he shall hear and promulgate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These being his functions, it becomes him to feel all confidence in himself, and to defer never to the popular cry. He and he only knows the world. The world of any moment is the merest appearance. Some great decorum, some fetich of a government, some ephemeral trade, or war, or man, is cried up by half mankind and cried down by the other half, as if all depended on this particular up or down. The odds are that the whole question is not worth the poorest thought which the scholar has lost in listening to the controversy. Let him not quit his belief that a popgun is a popgun, though the ancient and honorable of the earth affirm it to be the crack of doom. In silence, in steadiness, in severe abstraction, let him hold by himself; add observation to observation, patient of neglect, patient of reproach, and bide his own time happy enough if he can satisfy himself alone that this day he has seen something truly. Success treads on every right step. For the instinct is sure that prompts him to tell his brother what he thinks. He then learns that in going down into the secrets of his own mind he has descended into the secrets of all minds. He learns that he who has mastered any law in his private thoughts is master to that extent of all men whose language he speaks, and of all into whose language his own can be translated. The poet, in utter solitude remembering his spontaneous thoughts and recording them, is found to have recorded that which men in cities vast find true for them also. The orator distrusts at first the fitness of his frank confessions, his want of knowledge of the persons he addresses, until he finds that he is the complement of his hearers that they drink his words because he fulfills for them their own nature; the deeper he dives into his privatest, secretest presentiment, to his wonder he finds this is the most acceptable, most public and universally true. The people delight in it; the better part of every man feels This is my music; this is myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In self-trust all the virtues are comprehended. Free should the scholar be, free and brave. Free even to the definition of freedom, &amp;ldquo;without any hindrance that does not arise out of his own constitution.&amp;rdquo; Brave; for fear is a thing which a scholar by his very function puts behind him. Fear always springs from ignorance. It is a shame to him if his tranquility, amid dangerous times, arise from the presumption that like children and women his is a protected class; or if he seek a temporary peace by the diversion of his thoughts from politics or vexed questions, hiding his head like an ostrich in the flowering bushes, peeping into microscopes, and turning rhymes, as a boy whistles to keep his courage up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is the danger a danger still; so is the fear worse. Manlike let him turn and face it. Let him look into its eye and search its nature, inspect its origin see the whelping of this lion which lies no great way back; he will then find in himself a perfect comprehension of its nature and extent; he will have made his hands meet on the other side, and can henceforth defy it and pass on superior. The world is his who can see through its pretension. What deafness, what stone-blind custom, what overgrown error you behold is there only by sufferance by your sufferance. See it to be a lie, and you have already dealt it its mortal blow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we are the cowed we the trustless. It is a mischievous notion that we are come late into nature; that the world was finished a long time ago. As the world was plastic and fluid in the hands of God, so it is ever to so much of his attributes as we bring to it. To ignorance and sin it is flint. They adapt themselves to it as they may; but in proportion as a man has any thing in him divine, the firmament flows before him and takes his signet and form. Not he is great who can alter matter, but he who can alter my state of mind. They are the kings of the world who give the color of their present thought to all nature and all art, and persuade men, by the cheerful serenity of their carrying the matter, that this thing which they do is the apple which the ages have desired to pluck, now at last ripe, and inviting nations to the harvest. The great man makes the great thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever Macdonald sits, there is the head of the table. Linnus makes botany the most alluring of studies, and wins it from the farmer and the herb-woman: Davy, chemistry; and Cuvier, fossils. The day is always his who works in it with serenity and great aims. The unstable estimates of men crowd to him whose mind is filled with a truth, as the heaped waves of the Atlantic follow the moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this self-trust, the reason is deeper than can be fathomed darker than can be enlightened. I might not carry with me the feeling of my audience in stating my own belief. But I have already shown the ground of my hope, in adverting to the doctrine that man is one. I believe man has been wronged; he has wronged himself. He has almost lost the light that can lead him back to his prerogatives. Men are become of no account. Men in history, men in the world of today, are bugs, are spawn, and are called &amp;ldquo;the mass&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;the herd.&amp;rdquo; In a century, in a millenium, one or two men; that is to say, one or two approximations to the right state of every man. All the rest behold in the hero or the poet their own green and crude being ripened; yes, and are content to be less, so that may attain to its full stature. What a testimony, full of grandeur, full of pity, is borne to the demands of his own nature, by the poor clansman, the poor partisan, who rejoices in the glory of his chief! The poor and the low find some amends to their immense moral capacity, for their acquiescence in a political and social inferiority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are content to be brushed like flies from the path of a great person, so that justice shall be done by him to that common nature which it is the dearest desire of all to see enlarged and glorified. They sun themselves in the great man&amp;rsquo;s light, and feel it to be their own element. They cast the dignity of man from their downtrod selves upon the shoulders of a hero, and will perish to add one drop of blood to make that great heart beat, those giant sinews combat and conquer. He lives for us, and we live in him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men such as they are very naturally seek money or power; and power because it is as good as money the &amp;ldquo;spoils,&amp;rdquo; so called, &amp;ldquo;of office.&amp;rdquo; And why not? For they aspire to the highest, and this, in their sleep-walking, they dream is highest. Wake them and they shall quit the false good and leap to the true, and leave governments to clerks and desks. This revolution is to be wrought by the gradual domestication of the idea of Culture. The main enterprise of the world for splendor, for extent, is the upbuilding of a man. Here are the materials strewn along the ground. The private life of one man shall be a more illustrious monarchy, more formidable to its enemy, more sweet and serene in its influence to its friend, than any kingdom in history. For a man, rightly viewed, comprehendeth the particular natures of all men. Each philosopher, each bard, each actor has only done for me, as by a delegate, what one day I can do for myself. The books which once we valued more than the apple of the eye, we have quite exhausted. What is that but saying that we have come up with the point of view which the universal mind took through the eyes of one scribe; we have been that man, and have passed on. First, one, then another, we drain all cisterns, and waxing greater by all these supplies, we crave a better and a more abundant food. The man has never lived that can feed us ever. The human mind cannot be enshrined in a person who shall set a barrier on any one side to this unbounded, unboundable empire. It is one central fire, which, flaming now out of the lips of Etna, lightens the capes of Sicily, and now out of the throat of Vesuvius, illuminates the towers and vineyards of Naples. It is one light which beams out of a thousand stars. It is one soul which animates all men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have dwelt perhaps tediously upon this abstraction of the Scholar. I ought not to delay longer to add what I have to say of nearer reference to the time and to this country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, there is thought to be a difference in the ideas which predominate over successive epochs, and there are data for marking the genius of the Classic, of the Romantic, and now of the Reflective or Philosophical age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the views I have intimated of the oneness or the identity of the mind through all individuals, I do not much dwell on these differences. In fact, I believe each individual passes through all three. The boy is a Greek; the youth, romantic; the adult, reflective. I deny not, however, that a revolution in the leading idea may be distinctly enough traced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our age is bewailed as the age of Introversion. Must that needs be evil? We, it seems, are critical. We are embarrassed with second thoughts. We cannot enjoy anything for hankering to know whereof the pleasure consists. We are lined with eyes. We see with our feet. The time is infected with Hamlet&amp;rsquo;s unhappiness &amp;ldquo;Sicklied o&amp;rsquo;er with the pale cast of thought.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it so bad then? Sight is the last thing to be pitied. Would we be blind? Do we fear lest we should outsee nature and God, and drink truth dry? I look upon the discontent of the literary class as a mere announcement of the fact that they find themselves not in the state of mind of their fathers, and regret the coming state as untried; as a boy dreads the water before he has learned that he can swim. If there is any period one would desire to be born in, is it not the age of Revolution; when the old and the new stand side by side and admit of being compared; when the energies of all men are searched by fear and by hope; when the historic glories of the old can be compensated by the rich possibilities of the new era? This time, like all times, is a very good one, if we but know what to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read with some joy of the auspicious signs of the coming days, as they glimmer already through poetry and art, through philosophy and science, through church and state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these signs is the fact that the same movement which effected the elevation of what was called the lowest class in the state assumed in literature a very marked and as benign an aspect. Instead of the sublime and beautiful, the near, the low, the common, was explored and poetized. That which had been negligently trodden under foot by those who were harnessing and provisioning themselves for long journeys into far countries, is suddenly found to be richer than all foreign parts. The literature of the poor, the feelings of the child, the philosophy of the street, the meaning of household life, are the topics of the time. It is a great stride. It is a signis it not?of new vigor when the extremities are made active, when currents of warm life run into the hands and the feet. I ask not for the great, the remote, the romantic; what is doing in Italy or Arabia; what is Greek art, or Provenal minstrelsy; I embrace the common, I explore and sit at the feet of the familiar, the low. Give me insight into today, and you may have the antique and future worlds. What would we really know the meaning of? The meal in the firkin; the milk in the pan; the ballad in the street; the news of the boat; the glance of the eye; the form and the gait of the body show me the ultimate reason of these matters; show me the sublime presence of the highest spiritual cause lurking, as always it does lurk, in these suburbs and extremities of nature; let me see every trifle bristling with the polarity that ranges it instantly on an eternal law; and the shop, the plow, and the ledger referred to the like cause by which light undulates and poets sing; and the world lies no longer a dull miscellany and lumber-room, but has form and order: there is no trifle, there is no puzzle, but one design unites and animates the farthest pinnacle and the lowest trench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea has inspired the genius of Goldsmith, Burns, Cowper, and, in a newer time, of Goethe, Wordsworth, and Carlyle. This idea they have differently followed and with various success. In contrast with their writing, the style of Pope, of Johnson, of Gibbon, looks cold and pedantic. This writing is blood-warm. Man is surprised to find that things near are not less beautiful and wondrous than things remote. The near explains the far. The drop is a small ocean. A man is related to all nature. This perception of the worth of the vulgar is fruitful in discoveries. Goethe, in this very thing the most modern of the moderns, has shown us, as none ever did, the genius of the ancients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one man of genius who has done much for this philosophy of life, whose literary value has never yet been rightly estimated: I mean Emanuel Swedenborg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most imaginative of men, yet writing with the precision of a mathematician, he endeavored to engraft a purely philosophical Ethics on the popular Christianity of his time. Such an attempt of course must have difficulty which no genius could surmount. But he saw and showed the connexion between nature and the affections of the soul. He pierced the emblematic or spiritual character of the visible, audible, tangible world. Especially did his shade-loving muse hover over and interpret the lower parts of nature; he showed the mysterious bond that allies moral evil to the foul material forms, and has given in epical parables a theory of insanity, of beasts, of unclean and fearful things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sign of our times, also marked by an analogous political movement, is the new importance given to the single person. Everything that tends to insulate the individual to surround him with barriers of natural respect, so that each man shall feel the world is his, and man shall treat with man as a sovereign state with a sovereign statetends to true union as well as greatness. &amp;ldquo;I learned,&amp;rdquo; said the melancholy Pestalozzi, &amp;ldquo;that no man in God&amp;rsquo;s wide earth is either willing or able to help any other man.&amp;rdquo; Help must come from the bosom alone. The scholar is that man who must take up into himself all the ability of the time, all the contributions of the past, all the hopes of the future.
He must be an university of knowledges. If there be one lesson more than another that should pierce his ear, it isThe world is nothing, the man is all; in yourself is the law of all nature, and you know not yet how a globule of sap ascends; in yourself slumbers the whole of Reason; it is for you to know all; it is for you to dare all. Mr. President and Gentlemen, this confidence in the unsearched might of man belongs, by all motives, by all prophecy, by all preparation, to the American Scholar. We have listened too long to the courtly muses of Europe. The spirit of the American freeman is already suspected to be timid, imitative, tame. Public and private avarice make the air we breathe thick and fat. The scholar is decent, indolent, complaisant. See already the tragic consequence. The mind of this country, taught to aim at low objects, eats upon itself. There is no work for any one but the decorous and the complaisant. Young men of the fairest promise, who begin life upon our shores, inflated by the mountain winds, shined upon by all the stars of God, find the earth below not in unison with these, but are hindered from action by the disgust which the principles on which business is managed inspire, and turn drudges, or die of disgust, some of them suicides. What is the remedy? They did not yet see, and thousands of young men as hopeful now crowding to the barriers for the career do not yet see, that if the single man plant himself indomitably on his instincts, and there abide, the huge world will come round to him. Patience patience; with the shades of all the good and great for company; and for solace the perspective of your own infinite life; and for work the study and the communication of principles, the making those instincts prevalent, the conversion of the world.
Is it not the chief disgrace in the world, not to be an unit; not to be reckoned one character; not to yield that peculiar fruit which each man was created to bear, but to be reckoned in the gross, in the hundred, or the thousand, of the party, the section, to which we belong; and our opinion predicted geographically, as the north, or the south? Not so, brothers and friends please God, ours shall not be so. We will walk on our own feet; we will work with our own hands; we will speak our own minds. Then shall man be no longer a name for pity, for doubt, and for sensual indulgence. The dread of man and the love of man shall be a wall of defense and a wreath of joy around all. A nation of men will for the first time exist, because each believes himself inspired by the Divine Soul which also inspires all men.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>THESE ARE THE TIMES THAT TRY MEN&#39;S SOULS</title>
      <link>http://habedi.github.io/post/crisis-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 18:37:14 +0430</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://habedi.github.io/post/crisis-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Paine&#34;&gt;Thomas Paine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THESE are the times that try men&amp;rsquo;s souls. The summer soldier and the sunshine patriot will, in this crisis, shrink from the service of their country; but he that stands it now, deserves the love and thanks of man and woman. Tyranny, like hell, is not easily conquered; yet we have this consolation with us, that the harder the conflict, the more glorious the triumph. What we obtain too cheap, we esteem too lightly: it is dearness only that gives every thing its value. Heaven knows how to put a proper price upon its goods; and it would be strange indeed if so celestial an article as FREEDOM should not be highly rated. Britain, with an army to enforce her tyranny, has declared that she has a right (not only to TAX) but &amp;ldquo;to BIND us in ALL CASES WHATSOEVER,&amp;rdquo; and if being bound in that manner, is not slavery, then is there not such a thing as slavery upon earth. Even the expression is impious; for so unlimited a power can belong only to God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether the independence of the continent was declared too soon, or delayed too long, I will not now enter into as an argument; my own simple opinion is, that had it been eight months earlier, it would have been much better. We did not make a proper use of last winter, neither could we, while we were in a dependent state. However, the fault, if it were one, was all our own*; we have none to blame but ourselves. But no great deal is lost yet. All that Howe has been doing for this month past, is rather a ravage than a conquest, which the spirit of the Jerseys, a year ago, would have quickly repulsed, and which time and a little resolution will soon recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The present winter is worth an age, if rightly employed; but, if lost or neglected, the whole continent will partake of the evil; and there is no punishment that man does not deserve, be he who, or what, or where he will, that may be the means of sacrificing season so precious and useful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have as little superstition in me as any man living, but my secret opinion has ever been, and still is, that God Almighty will not give up a people to military destruction, or leave them unsupportedly to perish, who have so earnestly and so repeatedly sought to avoid the calamities of war, by every decent method which wisdom could invent. Neither have I so much of the infidel in me, as to suppose that He has relinquished the government of the world, and given us up to the care of devils; and as I do not, I cannot see on what grounds the king of Britain can look up to heaven for help against us: a common murderer, a highwayman, or a house-breaker, has as good a pretence as he.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Tis surprising to see how rapidly a panic will sometimes run through a country. All nations and ages have been subject to them. Britain has trembled like an ague at the report of a French fleet of flat-bottomed boats; and in the fourteenth [fifteenth] century the whole English army, after ravaging the kingdom of France, was driven back like men petrified with fear; and this brave exploit was performed by a few broken forces collected and headed by a woman, Joan of Arc. Would that heaven might inspire some Jersey maid to spirit up her countrymen, and save her fair fellow sufferers from ravage and ravishment! Yet panics, in some cases, have their uses; they produce as much good as hurt. Their duration is always short; the mind soon grows through them, and acquires a firmer habit than before. But their peculiar advantage is, that they are the touchstones of sincerity and hypocrisy, and bring things and men to light, which might otherwise have lain forever undiscovered. In fact, they have the same effect on secret traitors, which an imaginary apparition would have upon a private murderer. They sift out the hidden thoughts of man, and hold them up in public to the world. Many a disguised Tory has lately shown his head, that shall penitentially solemnize with curses the day on which Howe arrived upon the Delaware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was with the troops at Fort Lee, and marched with them to the edge of Pennsylvania, I am well acquainted with many circumstances, which those who live at a distance know but little or nothing of. Our situation there was exceedingly cramped, the place being a narrow neck of land between the North River and the Hackensack. Our force was inconsiderable, being not one-fourth so great as Howe could bring against us. We had no army at hand to have relieved the garrison, had we shut ourselves up and stood on our defence.
Our ammunition, light artillery, and the best part of our stores, had been removed, on the apprehension that Howe would endeavor to penetrate the Jerseys, in which case Fort Lee could be of no use to us; for it must occur to every thinking man, whether in the army or not, that these kind of field forts are only for temporary purposes, and last in use no longer than the enemy directs his force against the particular object which such forts are raised to defend. Such was our situation and condition at Fort Lee on the morning of the 20th of November, when an officer arrived with information that the enemy with 200 boats had landed about seven miles above; Major General [Nathaniel] Green, who commanded the garrison, immediately ordered them under arms, and sent express to General Washington at the town of Hackensack, distant by the way of the ferry = six miles.
Our first object was to secure the bridge over the Hackensack, which laid up the river between the enemy and us, about six miles from us, and three from them. General Washington arrived in about three-quarters of an hour, and marched at the head of the troops towards the bridge, which place I expected we should have a brush for; however, they did not choose to dispute it with us, and the greatest part of our troops went over the bridge, the rest over the ferry, except some which passed at a mill on a small creek, between the bridge and the ferry, and made their way through some marshy grounds up to the town of Hackensack, and there passed the river. We brought off as much baggage as the wagons could contain, the rest was lost. The simple object was to bring off the garrison, and march them on till they could be strengthened by the Jersey or Pennsylvania militia, so as to be enabled to make a stand. We staid four days at Newark, collected our out-posts with some of the Jersey militia, and marched out twice to meet the enemy, on being informed that they were advancing, though our numbers were greatly inferior to theirs. Howe, in my little opinion, committed a great error in generalship in not throwing a body of forces off from Staten Island through Amboy, by which means he might have seized all our stores at Brunswick, and intercepted our march into Pennsylvania; but if we believe the power of hell to be limited, we must likewise believe that their agents are under some providential control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shall not now attempt to give all the particulars of our retreat to the Delaware; suffice it for the present to say, that both officers and men, though greatly harassed and fatigued, frequently without rest, covering, or provision, the inevitable consequences of a long retreat, bore it with a manly and martial spirit. All their wishes centred in one, which was, that the country would turn out and help them to drive the enemy back. Voltaire has remarked that King William never appeared to full advantage but in difficulties and in action; the same remark may be made on General Washington, for the character fits him. There is a natural firmness in some minds which cannot be unlocked by trifles, but which, when unlocked, discovers a cabinet of fortitude; and I reckon it among those kind of public blessings, which we do not immediately see, that God hath blessed him with uninterrupted health, and given him a mind that can even flourish upon care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shall conclude this paper with some miscellaneous remarks on the state of our affairs; and shall begin with asking the following question, Why is it that the enemy have left the New England provinces, and made these middle ones the seat of war? The answer is easy: New England is not infested with Tories, and we are. I have been tender in raising the cry against these men, and used numberless arguments to show them their danger, but it will not do to sacrifice a world either to their folly or their baseness. The period is now arrived, in which either they or we must change our sentiments, or one or both must fall. And what is a Tory? Good God! what is he? I should not be afraid to go with a hundred Whigs against a thousand Tories, were they to attempt to get into arms. Every Tory is a coward; for servile, slavish, self-interested fear is the foundation of Toryism; and a man under such influence, though he may be cruel, never can be brave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, before the line of irrecoverable separation be drawn between us, let us reason the matter together: Your conduct is an invitation to the enemy, yet not one in a thousand of you has heart enough to join him. Howe is as much deceived by you as the American cause is injured by you. He expects you will all take up arms, and flock to his standard, with muskets on your shoulders. Your opinions are of no use to him, unless you support him personally, for &amp;lsquo;tis soldiers, and not Tories, that he wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I once felt all that kind of anger, which a man ought to feel, against the mean principles that are held by the Tories: a noted one, who kept a tavern at Amboy, was standing at his door, with as pretty a child in his hand, about eight or nine years old, as I ever saw, and after speaking his mind as freely as he thought was prudent, finished with this unfatherly expression, &amp;ldquo;Well! give me peace in my day.&amp;rdquo; Not a man lives on the continent but fully believes that a separation must some time or other finally take place, and a generous parent should have said, &amp;ldquo;If there must be trouble, let it be in my day, that my child may have peace;&amp;rdquo; and this single reflection, well applied, is sufficient to awaken every man to duty. Not a place upon earth might be so happy as America. Her situation is remote from all the wrangling world, and she has nothing to do but to trade with them. A man can distinguish himself between temper and principle, and I am as confident, as I am that God governs the world, that America will never be happy till she gets clear of foreign dominion. Wars, without ceasing, will break out till that period arrives, and the continent must in the end be conqueror; for though the flame of liberty may sometimes cease to shine, the coal can never expire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America did not, nor does not want force; but she wanted a proper application of that force. Wisdom is not the purchase of a day, and it is no wonder that we should err at the first setting off. From an excess of tenderness, we were unwilling to raise an army, and trusted our cause to the temporary defence of a well-meaning militia. A summer&amp;rsquo;s experience has now taught us better; yet with those troops, while they were collected, we were able to set bounds to the progress of the enemy, and, thank God! they are again assembling. I always considered militia as the best troops in the world for a sudden exertion, but they will not do for a long campaign. Howe, it is probable, will make an attempt on this city [Philadelphia]; should he fail on this side the Delaware, he is ruined. If he succeeds, our cause is not ruined. He stakes all on his side against a part on ours; admitting he succeeds, the consequence will be, that armies from both ends of the continent will march to assist their suffering friends in the middle states; for he cannot go everywhere, it is impossible.
I consider Howe as the greatest enemy the Tories have; he is bringing a war into their country, which, had it not been for him and partly for themselves, they had been clear of. Should he now be expelled, I wish with all the devotion of a Christian, that the names of Whig and Tory may never more be mentioned; but should the Tories give him encouragement to come, or assistance if he come, I as sincerely wish that our next year&amp;rsquo;s arms may expel them from the continent, and the Congress appropriate their possessions to the relief of those who have suffered in well-doing. A single successful battle next year will settle the whole. America could carry on a two years&amp;rsquo; war by the confiscation of the property of disaffected persons, and be made happy by their expulsion. Say not that this is revenge, call it rather the soft resentment of a suffering people, who, having no object in view but the good of all, have staked their own all upon a seemingly doubtful event. Yet it is folly to argue against determined hardness; eloquence may strike the ear, and the language of sorrow draw forth the tear of compassion, but nothing can reach the heart that is steeled with prejudice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quitting this class of men, I turn with the warm ardor of a friend to those who have nobly stood, and are yet determined to stand the matter out: I call not upon a few, but upon all: not on this state or that state, but on every state: up and help us; lay your shoulders to the wheel; better have too much force than too little, when so great an object is at stake. Let it be told to the future world, that in the depth of winter, when nothing but hope and virtue could survive, that the city and the country, alarmed at one common danger, came forth to meet and to repulse it. Say not that thousands are gone, turn out your tens of thousands; throw not the burden of the day upon Providence, but &amp;ldquo;show your faith by your works,&amp;rdquo; that God may bless you. It matters not where you live, or what rank of life you hold, the evil or the blessing will reach you all. The far and the near, the home counties and the back, the rich and the poor, will suffer or rejoice alike. The heart that feels not now is dead; the blood of his children will curse his cowardice, who shrinks back at a time when a little might have saved the whole, and made them happy.
I love the man that can smile in trouble, that can gather strength from distress, and grow brave by reflection. &amp;lsquo;Tis the business of little minds to shrink; but he whose heart is firm, and whose conscience approves his conduct, will pursue his principles unto death. My own line of reasoning is to myself as straight and clear as a ray of light. Not all the treasures of the world, so far as I believe, could have induced me to support an offensive war, for I think it murder; but if a thief breaks into my house, burns and destroys my property, and kills or threatens to kill me, or those that are in it, and to &amp;ldquo;bind me in all cases whatsoever&amp;rdquo; to his absolute will, am I to suffer it? What signifies it to me, whether he who does it is a king or a common man; my countryman or not my countryman; whether it be done by an individual villain, or an army of them? If we reason to the root of things we shall find no difference; neither can any just cause be assigned why we should punish in the one case and pardon in the other. Let them call me rebel and welcome, I feel no concern from it; but I should suffer the misery of devils, were I to make a whore of my soul by swearing allegiance to one whose character is that of a sottish, stupid, stubborn, worthless, brutish man. I conceive likewise a horrid idea in receiving mercy from a being, who at the last day shall be shrieking to the rocks and mountains to cover him, and fleeing with terror from the orphan, the widow, and the slain of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are cases which cannot be overdone by language, and this is one. There are persons, too, who see not the full extent of the evil which threatens them; they solace themselves with hopes that the enemy, if he succeed, will be merciful. It is the madness of folly, to expect mercy from those who have refused to do justice; and even mercy, where conquest is the object, is only a trick of war; the cunning of the fox is as murderous as the violence of the wolf, and we ought to guard equally against both. Howe&amp;rsquo;s first object is, partly by threats and partly by promises, to terrify or seduce the people to deliver up their arms and receive mercy. The ministry recommended the same plan to Gage, and this is what the tories call making their peace, &amp;ldquo;a peace which passeth all understanding&amp;rdquo; indeed! A peace which would be the immediate forerunner of a worse ruin than any we have yet thought of.
Ye men of Pennsylvania, do reason upon these things! Were the back counties to give up their arms, they would fall an easy prey to the Indians, who are all armed: this perhaps is what some Tories would not be sorry for. Were the home counties to deliver up their arms, they would be exposed to the resentment of the back counties who would then have it in their power to chastise their defection at pleasure. And were any one state to give up its arms, that state must be garrisoned by all Howe&amp;rsquo;s army of Britons and Hessians to preserve it from the anger of the rest. Mutual fear is the principal link in the chain of mutual love, and woe be to that state that breaks the compact. Howe is mercifully inviting you to barbarous destruction, and men must be either rogues or fools that will not see it. I dwell not upon the vapors of imagination; I bring reason to your ears, and, in language as plain as A, B, C, hold up truth to your eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank God, that I fear not. I see no real cause for fear. I know our situation well, and can see the way out of it. While our army was collected, Howe dared not risk a battle; and it is no credit to him that he decamped from the White Plains, and waited a mean opportunity to ravage the defenceless Jerseys; but it is great credit to us, that, with a handful of men, we sustained an orderly retreat for near an hundred miles, brought off our ammunition, all our field pieces, the greatest part of our stores, and had four rivers to pass. None can say that our retreat was precipitate, for we were near three weeks in performing it, that the country might have time to come in. Twice we marched back to meet the enemy, and remained out till dark. The sign of fear was not seen in our camp, and had not some of the cowardly and disaffected inhabitants spread false alarms through the country, the Jerseys had never been ravaged. Once more we are again collected and collecting; our new army at both ends of the continent is recruiting fast, and we shall be able to open the next campaign with sixty thousand men, well armed and clothed. This is our situation, and who will may know it. By perseverance and fortitude we have the prospect of a glorious issue; by cowardice and submission, the sad choice of a variety of evilsa ravaged countrya depopulated cityhabitations without safety, and slavery without hopeour homes turned into barracks and bawdy-houses for Hessians, and a future race to provide for, whose fathers we shall doubt of. Look on this picture and weep over it! and if there yet remains one thoughtless wretch who believes it not, let him suffer it unlamented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COMMON SENSE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;December 23, 1776.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IN PRAISE OF IDLENESS</title>
      <link>http://habedi.github.io/post/in-praise-of-idleness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 23:20:10 +0430</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://habedi.github.io/post/in-praise-of-idleness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertrand_Russell&#34;&gt;Bertrand Russell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most of my generation, I was brought up on the saying: &amp;lsquo;Satan finds some mischief for idle hands to do.&amp;rsquo; Being a highly virtuous child, I believed all that I was told, and acquired a conscience which has kept me working hard down to the present moment. But although my conscience has controlled my actions, my opinions have undergone a revolution. I think that there is far too much work done in the world, that immense harm is caused by the belief that work is virtuous, and that what needs to be preached in modern industrial countries is quite different from what always has been preached. Everyone knows the story of the traveler in Naples who saw twelve beggars lying in the sun (it was before the days of Mussolini), and offered a lira to the laziest of them. Eleven of them jumped up to claim it, so he gave it to the twelfth. this traveler was on the right lines. But in countries which do not enjoy Mediterranean sunshine idleness is more difficult, and a great public propaganda will be required to inaugurate it. I hope that, after reading the following pages, the leaders of the YMCA will start a campaign to induce good young men to do nothing. If so, I shall not have lived in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before advancing my own arguments for laziness, I must dispose of one which I cannot accept. Whenever a person who already has enough to live on proposes to engage in some everyday kind of job, such as school-teaching or typing, he or she is told that such conduct takes the bread out of other people&amp;rsquo;s mouths, and is therefore wicked. If this argument were valid, it would only be necessary for us all to be idle in order that we should all have our mouths full of bread. What people who say such things forget is that what a man earns he usually spends, and in spending he gives employment. As long as a man spends his income, he puts just as much bread into people&amp;rsquo;s mouths in spending as he takes out of other people&amp;rsquo;s mouths in earning. The real villain, from this point of view, is the man who saves. If he merely puts his savings in a stocking, like the proverbial French peasant, it is obvious that they do not give employment. If he invests his savings, the matter is less obvious, and different cases arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the commonest things to do with savings is to lend them to some Government. In view of the fact that the bulk of the public expenditure of most civilized Governments consists in payment for past wars or preparation for future wars, the man who lends his money to a Government is in the same position as the bad men in Shakespeare who hire murderers. The net result of the man&amp;rsquo;s economical habits is to increase the armed forces of the State to which he lends his savings. Obviously it would be better if he spent the money, even if he spent it in drink or gambling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I shall be told, the case is quite different when savings are invested in industrial enterprises. When such enterprises succeed, and produce something useful, this may be conceded. In these days, however, no one will deny that most enterprises fail. That means that a large amount of human labor, which might have been devoted to producing something that could be enjoyed, was expended on producing machines which, when produced, lay idle and did no good to anyone. The man who invests his savings in a concern that goes bankrupt is therefore injuring others as well as himself. If he spent his money, say, in giving parties for his friends, they (we may hope) would get pleasure, and so would all those upon whom he spent money, such as the butcher, the baker, and the bootlegger. But if he spends it (let us say) upon laying down rails for surface card in some place where surface cars turn out not to be wanted, he has diverted a mass of labor into channels where it gives pleasure to no one. Nevertheless, when he becomes poor through failure of his investment he will be regarded as a victim of undeserved misfortune, whereas the gay spendthrift, who has spent his money philanthropically, will be despised as a fool and a frivolous person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this is only preliminary. I want to say, in all seriousness, that a great deal of harm is being done in the modern world by belief in the virtuousness of work, and that the road to happiness and prosperity lies in an organized diminution of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all: what is work? Work is of two kinds: first, altering the position of matter at or near the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface relatively to other such matter; second, telling other people to do so. The first kind is unpleasant and ill paid; the second is pleasant and highly paid. The second kind is capable of indefinite extension: there are not only those who give orders, but those who give advice as to what orders should be given. Usually two opposite kinds of advice are given simultaneously by two organized bodies of men; this is called politics. The skill required for this kind of work is not knowledge of the subjects as to which advice is given, but knowledge of the art of persuasive speaking and writing, i.e. of advertising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout Europe, though not in America, there is a third class of men, more respected than either of the classes of workers. There are men who, through ownership of land, are able to make others pay for the privilege of being allowed to exist and to work. These landowners are idle, and I might therefore be expected to praise them. Unfortunately, their idleness is only rendered possible by the industry of others; indeed their desire for comfortable idleness is historically the source of the whole gospel of work. The last thing they have ever wished is that others should follow their example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning of civilization until the Industrial Revolution, a man could, as a rule, produce by hard work little more than was required for the subsistence of himself and his family, although his wife worked at least as hard as he did, and his children added their labor as soon as they were old enough to do so. The small surplus above bare necessaries was not left to those who produced it, but was appropriated by warriors and priests. In times of famine there was no surplus; the warriors and priests, however, still secured as much as at other times, with the result that many of the workers died of hunger. This system persisted in Russia until 1917 [1], and still persists in the East; in England, in spite of the Industrial Revolution, it remained in full force throughout the Napoleonic wars, and until a hundred years ago, when the new class of manufacturers acquired power. In America, the system came to an end with the Revolution, except in the South, where it persisted until the Civil War. A system which lasted so long and ended so recently has naturally left a profound impress upon men&amp;rsquo;s thoughts and opinions. Much that we take for granted about the desirability of work is derived from this system, and, being pre-industrial, is not adapted to the modern world. Modern technique has made it possible for leisure, within limits, to be not the prerogative of small privileged classes, but a right evenly distributed throughout the community. The morality of work is the morality of slaves, and the modern world has no need of slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that, in primitive communities, peasants, left to themselves, would not have parted with the slender surplus upon which the warriors and priests subsisted, but would have either produced less or consumed more. At first, sheer force compelled them to produce and part with the surplus. Gradually, however, it was found possible to induce many of them to accept an ethic according to which it was their duty to work hard, although part of their work went to support others in idleness. By this means the amount of compulsion required was lessened, and the expenses of government were diminished. To this day, 99 per cent of British wage-earners would be genuinely shocked if it were proposed that the King should not have a larger income than a working man. The conception of duty, speaking historically, has been a means used by the holders of power to induce others to live for the interests of their masters rather than for their own. Of course the holders of power conceal this fact from themselves by managing to believe that their interests are identical with the larger interests of humanity. Sometimes this is true; Athenian slave-owners, for instance, employed part of their leisure in making a permanent contribution to civilization which would have been impossible under a just economic system. Leisure is essential to civilization, and in former times leisure for the few was only rendered possible by the labors of the many. But their labors were valuable, not because work is good, but because leisure is good. And with modern technique it would be possible to distribute leisure justly without injury to civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern technique has made it possible to diminish enormously the amount of labor required to secure the necessaries of life for everyone. This was made obvious during the war. At that time all the men in the armed forces, and all the men and women engaged in the production of munitions, all the men and women engaged in spying, war propaganda, or Government offices connected with the war, were withdrawn from productive occupations. In spite of this, the general level of well-being among unskilled wage-earners on the side of the Allies was higher than before or since. The significance of this fact was concealed by finance: borrowing made it appear as if the future was nourishing the present. But that, of course, would have been impossible; a man cannot eat a loaf of bread that does not yet exist. The war showed conclusively that, by the scientific organization of production, it is possible to keep modern populations in fair comfort on a small part of the working capacity of the modern world. If, at the end of the war, the scientific organization, which had been created in order to liberate men for fighting and munition work, had been preserved, and the hours of the week had been cut down to four, all would have been well. Instead of that the old chaos was restored, those whose work was demanded were made to work long hours, and the rest were left to starve as unemployed. Why? Because work is a duty, and a man should not receive wages in proportion to what he has produced, but in proportion to his virtue as exemplified by his industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the morality of the Slave State, applied in circumstances totally unlike those in which it arose. No wonder the result has been disastrous. Let us take an illustration. Suppose that, at a given moment, a certain number of people are engaged in the manufacture of pins. They make as many pins as the world needs, working (say) eight hours a day. Someone makes an invention by which the same number of men can make twice as many pins: pins are already so cheap that hardly any more will be bought at a lower price. In a sensible world, everybody concerned in the manufacturing of pins would take to working four hours instead of eight, and everything else would go on as before. But in the actual world this would be thought demoralizing. The men still work eight hours, there are too many pins, some employers go bankrupt, and half the men previously concerned in making pins are thrown out of work. There is, in the end, just as much leisure as on the other plan, but half the men are totally idle while half are still overworked. In this way, it is insured that the unavoidable leisure shall cause misery all round instead of being a universal source of happiness. Can anything more insane be imagined?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that the poor should have leisure has always been shocking to the rich. In England, in the early nineteenth century, fifteen hours was the ordinary day&amp;rsquo;s work for a man; children sometimes did as much, and very commonly did twelve hours a day. When meddlesome busybodies suggested that perhaps these hours were rather long, they were told that work kept adults from drink and children from mischief. When I was a child, shortly after urban working men had acquired the vote, certain public holidays were established by law, to the great indignation of the upper classes. I remember hearing an old Duchess say: &amp;lsquo;What do the poor want with holidays? They ought to work.&amp;rsquo; People nowadays are less frank, but the sentiment persists, and is the source of much of our economic confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us, for a moment, consider the ethics of work frankly, without superstition. Every human being, of necessity, consumes, in the course of his life, a certain amount of the produce of human labor. Assuming, as we may, that labor is on the whole disagreeable, it is unjust that a man should consume more than he produces. Of course he may provide services rather than commodities, like a medical man, for example; but he should provide something in return for his board and lodging. to this extent, the duty of work must be admitted, but to this extent only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shall not dwell upon the fact that, in all modern societies outside the USSR, many people escape even this minimum amount of work, namely all those who inherit money and all those who marry money. I do not think the fact that these people are allowed to be idle is nearly so harmful as the fact that wage-earners are expected to overwork or starve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ordinary wage-earner worked four hours a day, there would be enough for everybody and no unemployment &amp;ndash; assuming a certain very moderate amount of sensible organization. This idea shocks the well-to-do, because they are convinced that the poor would not know how to use so much leisure. In America men often work long hours even when they are well off; such men, naturally, are indignant at the idea of leisure for wage-earners, except as the grim punishment of unemployment; in fact, they dislike leisure even for their sons. Oddly enough, while they wish their sons to work so hard as to have no time to be civilized, they do not mind their wives and daughters having no work at all. the snobbish admiration of uselessness, which, in an aristocratic society, extends to both sexes, is, under a plutocracy, confined to women; this, however, does not make it any more in agreement with common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wise use of leisure, it must be conceded, is a product of civilization and education. A man who has worked long hours all his life will become bored if he becomes suddenly idle. But without a considerable amount of leisure a man is cut off from many of the best things. There is no longer any reason why the bulk of the population should suffer this deprivation; only a foolish asceticism, usually vicarious, makes us continue to insist on work in excessive quantities now that the need no longer exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new creed which controls the government of Russia, while there is much that is very different from the traditional teaching of the West, there are some things that are quite unchanged. The attitude of the governing classes, and especially of those who conduct educational propaganda, on the subject of the dignity of labor, is almost exactly that which the governing classes of the world have always preached to what were called the &amp;lsquo;honest poor&amp;rsquo;. Industry, sobriety, willingness to work long hours for distant advantages, even submissiveness to authority, all these reappear; moreover authority still represents the will of the Ruler of the Universe, Who, however, is now called by a new name, Dialectical Materialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The victory of the proletariat in Russia has some points in common with the victory of the feminists in some other countries. For ages, men had conceded the superior saintliness of women, and had consoled women for their inferiority by maintaining that saintliness is more desirable than power. At last the feminists decided that they would have both, since the pioneers among them believed all that the men had told them about the desirability of virtue, but not what they had told them about the worthlessness of political power. A similar thing has happened in Russia as regards manual work. For ages, the rich and their sycophants have written in praise of &amp;lsquo;honest toil&amp;rsquo;, have praised the simple life, have professed a religion which teaches that the poor are much more likely to go to heaven than the rich, and in general have tried to make manual workers believe that there is some special nobility about altering the position of matter in space, just as men tried to make women believe that they derived some special nobility from their sexual enslavement. In Russia, all this teaching about the excellence of manual work has been taken seriously, with the result that the manual worker is more honored than anyone else. What are, in essence, revivalist appeals are made, but not for the old purposes: they are made to secure shock workers for special tasks. Manual work is the ideal which is held before the young, and is the basis of all ethical teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the present, possibly, this is all to the good. A large country, full of natural resources, awaits development, and has has to be developed with very little use of credit. In these circumstances, hard work is necessary, and is likely to bring a great reward. But what will happen when the point has been reached where everybody could be comfortable without working long hours?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West, we have various ways of dealing with this problem. We have no attempt at economic justice, so that a large proportion of the total produce goes to a small minority of the population, many of whom do no work at all. Owing to the absence of any central control over production, we produce hosts of things that are not wanted. We keep a large percentage of the working population idle, because we can dispense with their labor by making the others overwork. When all these methods prove inadequate, we have a war: we cause a number of people to manufacture high explosives, and a number of others to explode them, as if we were children who had just discovered fireworks. By a combination of all these devices we manage, though with difficulty, to keep alive the notion that a great deal of severe manual work must be the lot of the average man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Russia, owing to more economic justice and central control over production, the problem will have to be differently solved. the rational solution would be, as soon as the necessaries and elementary comforts can be provided for all, to reduce the hours of labor gradually, allowing a popular vote to decide, at each stage, whether more leisure or more goods were to be preferred. But, having taught the supreme virtue of hard work, it is difficult to see how the authorities can aim at a paradise in which there will be much leisure and little work. It seems more likely that they will find continually fresh schemes, by which present leisure is to be sacrificed to future productivity. I read recently of an ingenious plan put forward by Russian engineers, for making the White Sea and the northern coasts of Siberia warm, by putting a dam across the Kara Sea. An admirable project, but liable to postpone proletarian comfort for a generation, while the nobility of toil is being displayed amid the ice-fields and snowstorms of the Arctic Ocean. This sort of thing, if it happens, will be the result of regarding the virtue of hard work as an end in itself, rather than as a means to a state of affairs in which it is no longer needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that moving matter about, while a certain amount of it is necessary to our existence, is emphatically not one of the ends of human life. If it were, we should have to consider every navvy superior to Shakespeare. We have been misled in this matter by two causes. One is the necessity of keeping the poor contented, which has led the rich, for thousands of years, to preach the dignity of labor, while taking care themselves to remain undignified in this respect. The other is the new pleasure in mechanism, which makes us delight in the astonishingly clever changes that we can produce on the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface. Neither of these motives makes any great appeal to the actual worker. If you ask him what he thinks the best part of his life, he is not likely to say: &amp;lsquo;I enjoy manual work because it makes me feel that I am fulfilling man&amp;rsquo;s noblest task, and because I like to think how much man can transform his planet. It is true that my body demands periods of rest, which I have to fill in as best I may, but I am never so happy as when the morning comes and I can return to the toil from which my contentment springs.&amp;rsquo; I have never heard working men say this sort of thing. They consider work, as it should be considered, a necessary means to a livelihood, and it is from their leisure that they derive whatever happiness they may enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be said that, while a little leisure is pleasant, men would not know how to fill their days if they had only four hours of work out of the twenty-four. In so far as this is true in the modern world, it is a condemnation of our civilization; it would not have been true at any earlier period. There was formerly a capacity for light-heartedness and play which has been to some extent inhibited by the cult of efficiency. The modern man thinks that everything ought to be done for the sake of something else, and never for its own sake. Serious-minded persons, for example, are continually condemning the habit of going to the cinema, and telling us that it leads the young into crime. But all the work that goes to producing a cinema is respectable, because it is work, and because it brings a money profit. The notion that the desirable activities are those that bring a profit has made everything topsy-turvy. The butcher who provides you with meat and the baker who provides you with bread are praiseworthy, because they are making money; but when you enjoy the food they have provided, you are merely frivolous, unless you eat only to get strength for your work. Broadly speaking, it is held that getting money is good and spending money is bad. Seeing that they are two sides of one transaction, this is absurd; one might as well maintain that keys are good, but keyholes are bad. Whatever merit there may be in the production of goods must be entirely derivative from the advantage to be obtained by consuming them. The individual, in our society, works for profit; but the social purpose of his work lies in the consumption of what he produces. It is this divorce between the individual and the social purpose of production that makes it so difficult for men to think clearly in a world in which profit-making is the incentive to industry. We think too much of production, and too little of consumption. One result is that we attach too little importance to enjoyment and simple happiness, and that we do not judge production by the pleasure that it gives to the consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I suggest that working hours should be reduced to four, I am not meaning to imply that all the remaining time should necessarily be spent in pure frivolity. I mean that four hours&amp;rsquo; work a day should entitle a man to the necessities and elementary comforts of life, and that the rest of his time should be his to use as he might see fit. It is an essential part of any such social system that education should be carried further than it usually is at present, and should aim, in part, at providing tastes which would enable a man to use leisure intelligently. I am not thinking mainly of the sort of things that would be considered &amp;lsquo;highbrow&amp;rsquo;. Peasant dances have died out except in remote rural areas, but the impulses which caused them to be cultivated must still exist in human nature. The pleasures of urban populations have become mainly passive: seeing cinemas, watching football matches, listening to the radio, and so on. This results from the fact that their active energies are fully taken up with work; if they had more leisure, they would again enjoy pleasures in which they took an active part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, there was a small leisure class and a larger working class. The leisure class enjoyed advantages for which there was no basis in social justice; this necessarily made it oppressive, limited its sympathies, and caused it to invent theories by which to justify its privileges. These facts greatly diminished its excellence, but in spite of this drawback it contributed nearly the whole of what we call civilization. It cultivated the arts and discovered the sciences; it wrote the books, invented the philosophies, and refined social relations. Even the liberation of the oppressed has usually been inaugurated from above. Without the leisure class, mankind would never have emerged from barbarism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method of a leisure class without duties was, however, extraordinarily wasteful. None of the members of the class had to be taught to be industrious, and the class as a whole was not exceptionally intelligent. The class might produce one Darwin, but against him had to be set tens of thousands of country gentlemen who never thought of anything more intelligent than fox-hunting and punishing poachers. At present, the universities are supposed to provide, in a more systematic way, what the leisure class provided accidentally and as a by-product. This is a great improvement, but it has certain drawbacks. University life is so different from life in the world at large that men who live in academic milieu tend to be unaware of the preoccupations and problems of ordinary men and women; moreover their ways of expressing themselves are usually such as to rob their opinions of the influence that they ought to have upon the general public. Another disadvantage is that in universities studies are organized, and the man who thinks of some original line of research is likely to be discouraged. Academic institutions, therefore, useful as they are, are not adequate guardians of the interests of civilization in a world where everyone outside their walls is too busy for unutilitarian pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world where no one is compelled to work more than four hours a day, every person possessed of scientific curiosity will be able to indulge it, and every painter will be able to paint without starving, however excellent his pictures may be. Young writers will not be obliged to draw attention to themselves by sensational pot-boilers, with a view to acquiring the economic independence needed for monumental works, for which, when the time at last comes, they will have lost the taste and capacity. Men who, in their professional work, have become interested in some phase of economics or government, will be able to develop their ideas without the academic detachment that makes the work of university economists often seem lacking in reality. Medical men will have the time to learn about the progress of medicine, teachers will not be exasperatedly struggling to teach by routine methods things which they learnt in their youth, which may, in the interval, have been proved to be untrue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, there will be happiness and joy of life, instead of frayed nerves, weariness, and dyspepsia. The work exacted will be enough to make leisure delightful, but not enough to produce exhaustion. Since men will not be tired in their spare time, they will not demand only such amusements as are passive and vapid. At least one per cent will probably devote the time not spent in professional work to pursuits of some public importance, and, since they will not depend upon these pursuits for their livelihood, their originality will be unhampered, and there will be no need to conform to the standards set by elderly pundits. But it is not only in these exceptional cases that the advantages of leisure will appear. Ordinary men and women, having the opportunity of a happy life, will become more kindly and less persecuting and less inclined to view others with suspicion. The taste for war will die out, partly for this reason, and partly because it will involve long and severe work for all. Good nature is, of all moral qualities, the one that the world needs most, and good nature is the result of ease and security, not of a life of arduous struggle. Modern methods of production have given us the possibility of ease and security for all; we have chosen, instead, to have overwork for some and starvation for others. Hitherto we have continued to be as energetic as we were before there were machines; in this we have been foolish, but there is no reason to go on being foolish forever.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WHAT IS ENLIGHTENMENTS?</title>
      <link>http://habedi.github.io/post/what-is-enlightenment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 23:20:10 +0430</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://habedi.github.io/post/what-is-enlightenment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&#34;http://https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immanuel_Kant&#34;&gt;Immanuel Kant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enlightenment is man&amp;rsquo;s emergence from his self-imposed nonage. Nonage is the inability to use one&amp;rsquo;s own understanding without another&amp;rsquo;s guidance. This nonage is self-imposed if its cause lies not in lack of understanding but in indecision and lack of courage to use one&amp;rsquo;s own mind without another&amp;rsquo;s guidance. Dare to know! (Sapere aude.) &amp;ldquo;Have the courage to use your own understanding,&amp;rdquo; is therefore the motto of the enlightenment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laziness and cowardice are the reasons why such a large part of mankind gladly remain minors all their lives, long after nature has freed them from external guidance. They are the reasons why it is so easy for others to set themselves up as guardians. It is so comfortable to be a minor. If I have a book that thinks for me, a pastor who acts as my conscience, a physician who prescribes my diet, and so on&amp;ndash;then I have no need to exert myself. I have no need to think, if only I can pay; others will take care of that disagreeable business for me. Those guardians who have kindly taken supervision upon themselves see to it that the overwhelming majority of mankind&amp;ndash;among them the entire fair sex&amp;ndash;should consider the step to maturity, not only as hard, but as extremely dangerous. First, these guardians make their domestic cattle stupid and carefully prevent the docile creatures from taking a single step without the leading-strings to which they have fastened them. Then they show them the danger that would threaten them if they should try to walk by themselves. Now this danger is really not very great; after stumbling a few times they would, at last, learn to walk. However, examples of such failures intimidate and generally discourage all further attempts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus it is very difficult for the individual to work himself out of the nonage which has become almost second nature to him. He has even grown to like it, and is at first really incapable of using his own understanding because he has never been permitted to try it. Dogmas and formulas, these mechanical tools designed for reasonable use&amp;ndash;or rather abuse&amp;ndash;of his natural gifts, are the fetters of an everlasting nonage. The man who casts them off would make an uncertain leap over the narrowest ditch, because he is not used to such free movement. That is why there are only a few men who walk firmly, and who have emerged from nonage by cultivating their own minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more nearly possible, however, for the public to enlighten itself; indeed, if it is only given freedom, enlightenment is almost inevitable. There will always be a few independent thinkers, even among the self-appointed guardians of the multitude. Once such men have thrown off the yoke of nonage, they will spread about them the spirit of a reasonable appreciation of man&amp;rsquo;s value and of his duty to think for himself. It is especially to be noted that the public which was earlier brought under the yoke by these men afterwards forces these very guardians to remain in submission, if it is so incited by some of its guardians who are themselves incapable of any enlightenment. That shows how pernicious it is to implant prejudices: they will eventually revenge themselves upon their authors or their authors&amp;rsquo; descendants. Therefore, a public can achieve enlightenment only slowly. A revolution may bring about the end of a personal despotism or of avaricious tyrannical oppression, but never a true reform of modes of thought. New prejudices will serve, in place of the old, as guide lines for the unthinking multitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This enlightenment requires nothing but freedom&amp;ndash;and the most innocent of all that may be called &amp;ldquo;freedom&amp;rdquo;: freedom to make public use of one&amp;rsquo;s reason in all matters. Now I hear the cry from all sides: &amp;ldquo;Do not argue!&amp;rdquo; The officer says: &amp;ldquo;Do not argue&amp;ndash;drill!&amp;rdquo; The tax collector: &amp;ldquo;Do not argue&amp;ndash;pay!&amp;rdquo; The pastor: &amp;ldquo;Do not argue&amp;ndash;believe!&amp;rdquo; Only one ruler in the world says: &amp;ldquo;Argue as much as you please, but obey!&amp;rdquo; We find restrictions on freedom everywhere. But which restriction is harmful to enlightenment? Which restriction is innocent, and which advances enlightenment? I reply: the public use of one&amp;rsquo;s reason must be free at all times, and this alone can bring enlightenment to mankind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the private use of reason may frequently be narrowly restricted without especially hindering the progress of enlightenment. By &amp;ldquo;public use of one&amp;rsquo;s reason&amp;rdquo; I mean that use which a man, as scholar, makes of it before the reading public. I call &amp;ldquo;private use&amp;rdquo; that use which a man makes of his reason in a civic post that has been entrusted to him. In some affairs affecting the interest of the community a certain [governmental] mechanism is necessary in which some members of the community remain passive. This creates an artificial unanimity which will serve the fulfillment of public objectives, or at least keep these objectives from being destroyed. Here arguing is not permitted: one must obey. Insofar as a part of this machine considers himself at the same time a member of a universal community&amp;ndash;a world society of citizens&amp;ndash;(let us say that he thinks of himself as a scholar rationally addressing his public through his writings) he may indeed argue, and the affairs with which he is associated in part as a passive member will not suffer.
Thus it would be very unfortunate if an officer on duty and under orders from his superiors should want to criticize the appropriateness or utility of his orders. He must obey. But as a scholar he could not rightfully be prevented from taking notice of the mistakes in the military service and from submitting his views to his public for its judgment. The citizen cannot refuse to pay the taxes levied upon him; indeed, impertinent censure of such taxes could be punished as a scandal that might cause general disobedience. Nevertheless, this man does not violate the duties of a citizen if, as a scholar, he publicly expresses his objections to the impropriety or possible injustice of such levies. A pastor, too, is bound to preach to his congregation in accord with the doctrines of the church which he serves, for he was ordained on that condition. But as a scholar he has full freedom, indeed the obligation, to communicate to his public all his carefully examined and constructive thoughts concerning errors in that doctrine and his proposals concerning improvement of religious dogma and church institutions. This is nothing that could burden his conscience. For what he teaches in pursuance of his office as representative of the church, he represents as something which he is not free to teach as he sees it.
He speaks as one who is employed to speak in the name and under the orders of another. He will say: &amp;ldquo;Our church teaches this or that; these are the proofs which it employs.&amp;rdquo; Thus he will benefit his congregation as much as possible by presenting doctrines to which he may not subscribe with full conviction. He can commit himself to teach them because it is not completely impossible that they may contain hidden truth. In any event, he has found nothing in the doctrines that contradicts the heart of religion. For if he believed that such contradictions existed he would not be able to administer his office with a clear conscience. He would have to resign it. Therefore the use which a scholar makes of his reason before the congregation that employs him is only a private use, for no matter how sizable, this is only a domestic audience. In view of this he, as preacher, is not free and ought not to be free, since he is carrying out the orders of others. On the other hand, as the scholar who speaks to his own public (the world) through his writings, the minister in the public use of his reason enjoys unlimited freedom to use his own reason and to speak for himself. That the spiritual guardians of the people should themselves be treated as minors is an absurdity which would result in perpetuating absurdities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But should a society of ministers, say a Church Council, &amp;hellip; have the right to commit itself by oath to a certain unalterable doctrine, in order to secure perpetual guardianship over all its members and through them over the people? I say that this is quite impossible. Such a contract, concluded to keep all further enlightenment from humanity, is simply null and void even if it should be confirmed by the sovereign power, by parliaments, and the most solemn treaties. An epoch cannot conclude a pact that will commit succeeding ages, prevent them from increasing their significant insights, purging themselves of errors, and generally progressing in enlightenment. That would be a crime against human nature whose proper destiny lies precisely in such progress. Therefore, succeeding ages are fully entitled to repudiate such decisions as unauthorized and outrageous. The touchstone of all those decisions that may be made into law for a people lies in this question: Could a people impose such a law upon itself? Now it might be possible to introduce a certain order for a definite short period of time in expectation of better order.
But, while this provisional order continues, each citizen (above all, each pastor acting as a scholar) should be left free to publish his criticisms of the faults of existing institutions. This should continue until public understanding of these matters has gone so far that, by uniting the voices of many (although not necessarily all) scholars, reform proposals could be brought before the sovereign to protect those congregations which had decided according to their best lights upon an altered religious order, without, however, hindering those who want to remain true to the old institutions. But to agree to a perpetual religious constitution which is not publicly questioned by anyone would be, as it were, to annihilate a period of time in the progress of man&amp;rsquo;s improvement. This must be absolutely forbidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A man may postpone his own enlightenment, but only for a limited period of time. And to give up enlightenment altogether, either for oneself or one&amp;rsquo;s descendants, is to violate and to trample upon the sacred rights of man. What a people may not decide for itself may even less be decided for it by a monarch, for his reputation as a ruler consists precisely in the way in which he unites the will of the whole people within his own. If he only sees to it that all true or supposed [religious] improvement remains in step with the civic order, he can for the rest leave his subjects alone to do what they find necessary for the salvation of their souls. Salvation is none of his business; it is his business to prevent one man from forcibly keeping another from determining and promoting his salvation to the best of his ability. Indeed, it would be prejudicial to his majesty if he meddled in these matters and supervised the writings in which his subjects seek to bring their [religious] views into the open, even when he does this from his own highest insight, because then he exposes himself to the reproach: Caesar non est supra grammaticos. It is worse when he debases his sovereign power so far as to support the spiritual despotism of a few tyrants in his state over the rest of his subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we ask, Are we now living in an enlightened age? the answer is, No, but we live in an age of enlightenment. As matters now stand it is still far from true that men are already capable of using their own reason in religious matters confidently and correctly without external guidance. Still, we have some obvious indications that the field of working toward the goal [of religious truth] is now opened. What is more, the hindrances against general enlightenment or the emergence from self-imposed nonage are gradually diminishing. In this respect this is the age of the enlightenment and the century of Frederick [the Great].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prince ought not to deem it beneath his dignity to state that he considers it his duty not to dictate anything to his subjects in religious matters, but to leave them complete freedom. If he repudiates the arrogant word &amp;ldquo;tolerant&amp;rdquo;, he is himself enlightened; he deserves to be praised by a grateful world and posterity as that man who was the first to liberate mankind from dependence, at least on the government, and let everybody use his own reason in matters of conscience. Under his reign, honorable pastors, acting as scholars and regardless of the duties of their office, can freely and openly publish their ideas to the world for inspection, although they deviate here and there from accepted doctrine. This is even more true of every person not restrained by any oath of office. This spirit of freedom is spreading beyond the boundaries [of Prussia] even where it has to struggle against the external hindrances established by a government that fails to grasp its true interest. [Frederick&amp;rsquo;s Prussia] is a shining example that freedom need not cause the least worry concerning public order or the unity of the community. When one does not deliberately attempt to keep men in barbarism, they will gradually work out of that condition by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have emphasized the main point of the enlightenment-man&amp;rsquo;s emergence from his self-imposed nonage&amp;ndash;primarily in religious matters, because our rulers have no interest in playing the guardian to their subjects in the arts and sciences. Above all, nonage in religion is not only the most harmful but the most dishonorable. But the disposition of a sovereign ruler who favors freedom in the arts and sciences goes even further: he knows that there is no danger in permitting his subjects to make public use of their reason and to publish their ideas concerning a better constitution, as well as candid criticism of existing basic laws. We already have a striking example [of such freedom], and no monarch can match the one whom we venerate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But only the man who is himself enlightened, who is not afraid of shadows, and who commands at the same time a well disciplined and numerous army as guarantor of public peace&amp;ndash;only he can say what [the sovereign of] a free state cannot dare to say: &amp;ldquo;Argue as much as you like, and about what you like, but obey!&amp;rdquo; Thus we observe here as elsewhere in human affairs, in which almost everything is paradoxical, a surprising and unexpected course of events: a large degree of civic freedom appears to be of advantage to the intellectual freedom of the people, yet at the same time it establishes insurmountable barriers. A lesser degree of civic freedom, however, creates room to let that free spirit expand to the limits of its capacity. Nature, then, has carefully cultivated the seed within the hard core&amp;ndash;namely the urge for and the vocation of free thought. And this free thought gradually reacts back on the modes of thought of the people, and men become more and more capable of acting in freedom. At last free thought acts even on the fundamentals of government and the state finds it agreeable to treat man, who is now more than a machine, in accord with his dignity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Translated by Mary C. Smith&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A FEW QUOTES</title>
      <link>http://habedi.github.io/post/a-few-quotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2016 22:02:14 +0430</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://habedi.github.io/post/a-few-quotes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:black; font-family:Consolas; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;ve just finished compiling a list of quotes, mostly from ancient Roman philosophers and orators and poets such as Horace and Vergil and Cicero that I want to share with you folks, so without further ado let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at these lovely gems: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;bonus vir semper tiro ~ a good man is always learning &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;carpe diem, quam minimum (or minime) credula postero (Horace) ~ seize the day, trusting little in tomorrow &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;causarum ignoratio in re nova mirationem facit (Cicero) ~ in extraordinary events ignorance of their causes produces astonishment &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;the availability of books is not the same as reading them, nor reading the same as understanding them (Tristram Shandy) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;winning is a good habit;0) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;your life has a limit, but knowledge has none; if you use what is limited to pursue what has no limit, you will be in danger (Zhuangzi) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;exigua pars est vitae quam nos vivimus (Seneca) ~ the part of life that we really live is short &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;natura vero nihil hominibus brevitate vitae praestitit melius (Pliny the Elder) ~ nature has granted man no better gift than the brevity of life &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;nihil scire est vita jucundissima ~ to know nothing at all is the happiest life &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;insanus omnis furere credit caeteros (Publilius Syrus) ~ madman thinks all others are insane &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;vivere est cogitare (Cicero) ~ to live is to think &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;despicio terrena et solem contemplor ~ I despise earthly things and contemplate the sun &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;cineres credis curare sepultos? ~ do you think that the ashes of the dead can beaffected by this? (i.e., do you think the dead can be affected by the thoughts or actions of the living?) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;nunquam sero te venisse putabo, si salvus veneris (Cicero) ~ I shall never think that you are late arriving, provided you arrive safely &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;omnia jam fient, fieri quae posse negabam; et nihil est de quo non sit habendafides (Ovid) ~ all things will now come to pass that I used to think impossible; and there is nothing that we may not hope to see take place &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;sed quis custodiet ipsos custodes? (Juvenal) ~ but who will guard the guardians themselves &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;acclinus falsis animus meliora recusat (Horace) ~ the mind attracted by what is false refuses better things &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;cum corpore mentem crescere sentimus pariterque senescere (Lucretius) ~ we find that, as the mind strengthens with the body, it decays with it in like manner &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;pulchra mulier nuda erit quam purpurata pulchrior (Plautus) ~ a beautiful woman is more beautiful undressed than dressed in fine purple &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;bella detesta matribus (Horace) ~ wars, the horror of mothers &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;quocunque trahunt Fata, sequamur (Vergil) ~ wherever the Fates direct us let us follow &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;remember, video games qualify as art (myself obviously;0)) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt;pulvis et umbra sumus (Horace) ~ we are but dust and shadow &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:purple; font-family:Arial; font-size:1.2em;&#34;&gt; quid opus est partes deflere? tota flebilis vita est (Seneca) ~ What need is there to weep over parts of life? The whole of it calls for tears &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>